<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-11-01T22:59:29-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Portfolio</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why Developers and Designers need to engage with a Community</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/08/09/Why-developers-and-designers-need-to-engage-in-a-community/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Developers and Designers need to engage with a Community" /><published>2016-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/08/09/Why-developers-and-designers-need-to-engage-in-a-community</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/08/09/Why-developers-and-designers-need-to-engage-in-a-community/">&lt;p&gt;Here we unpackage why engaging in communities is important for developers and designers, especially for those starting out a an entrepreneur. Along with going over what the different communities like Seanwes and the DevTips Community have to offer and why they’re a gold mine for new creatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-do-you-usually-turn-when-you-need-to-ask-a-question&quot;&gt;Where do you usually turn when you need to ask a question?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine yourself being new to your career as a designer. That could mean that you are just rolling out of college or high school wondering what’s next, or you could be like me who was tired of doing the current work and was looking for a change. What no one tells you is that it’s hard to sift through the noise of what information is out there in the world. There are countless resources all over the internet about whatever it is you need to know, whether it can actually help you or not. And when it comes to design questions that I needed answers for, I had two people in my life who kind of know about what I’m trying to learn. Most of the time though, I’ve had to turn to the almighty Google and throw it questions like feeding fish to an army of angry penguins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many times while searching for information about building websites, I have had to turn to YouTube to figure out what I need to do next. The answers that I got was unhelpful until I stumbled upon the video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XnWIperMy08&quot;&gt;“How to Code a Responsive HTML Email.”&lt;/a&gt; Which, I admit, is an odd one to jump into. This cool cat’s name is Travis and he’s the host of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://devtipsshow.com/&quot;&gt;DevTips Show&lt;/a&gt;. I usually look at YouTube videos like these when I want to learn something new even though it can be as productive as it is unproductive.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/post-devtips/htmlEmails.png&quot; alt=&quot;Searching 'How do I style HTML emails?'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-why-did-this-change-everything-for-me&quot;&gt;So why did this change everything for me?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the time you find yourself alone with no one you can get answers from. That can be pretty difficult when you need to grow in a certain area. What do you do? &lt;em&gt;Do you go back to school? Do you call up your aunt who did graphic design in the 80’s?&lt;/em&gt; Maybe the best solution is seek out people doing the same thing you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had found that just watching videos wasn’t cutting it. I needed help with things that I was learning, had so many questions. I looked to what seemed like random corners of the internet for answering questions and even resorted to asking people with personal websites using their contact forms. (Yes, I was that committed.) When I finally found the answer to something I was looking for, I just happened to watch the end of another DevTips video, the host, Travis, talked again about the DevTips Community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-does-a-community-do&quot;&gt;So what does a community do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A community is a group of people who collectively come together around a certain purpose or walk of life. They form when at least two people are drawn to some idea or interest. It is the first time you realize that you aren’t the only one who needs  the same answers you are looking for. People have personalized experiences that to them may seem inconsequential but to another person, that experience shared could mean saving years of their life searching for that same thing. For the commune of web designers and developers, the ability to be able to convene together and ask for help is invaluable. Each new idea or niche is a seed that grows into it’s own community eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this forms how you think of communities this helps you see that they are all around you. Maybe it’s the yoga group that meets every week, maybe it’s the church down the road, or your high school buddies hanging out at the parking lot of a Safeway (you do you, Arlington). I know that there are meetups for all types of careers, code languages, ideas, religions in every town. People convene in locations all around you and you might not even see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of being part of communities are that you have access to some of the brilliant minds of others; if it’s online, that could be at any given point from any type of life from any place on the globe. They help you sift through that sea of emptiness on the internet by sharing what they know about their work. They take on the questions that you ask and help work on solutions. You’ll start to find that you have answers to some of the things being asked too. By sharing what you know, you may not just help the person who asked, but find that you’re able to help yourself solidify what you know, or even realize what you still have to learn.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/post-devtips/community.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Community hangout for people who love to do things, I guess&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-if-communities-are-great-what-are-some-of-the-ones-that-youve-seen-or-been-part-of&quot;&gt;So if communities are great, what are some of the ones that you’ve seen or been part of&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The DevTips Community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Megamaker group&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Seanwes Community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Been to dribbble meetups and freeCodeCamp meetups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-devtips-and-the-devtips-community&quot;&gt;What is DevTips and the DevTips Community?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;callout&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;DevTips is a weekly YouTube show that focuses on web development and design, hosted by Travis Neilson.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quoting Travis himself, DevTips is “a weekly YouTube show that focuses on web development and design.” It’s focused on exploring the front end development side of making website designs. It’s pure gold to someone like me who’s wondered how certain things are done with the crazy and unpredictable CSS and JavaScript (ECMAScript). This show is hosted by Travis Nielsen, now (at the time of this writing) an employee at Google who has been doing awesome videos for the past few years. Travis has built a large following of over 125,000 subscribers (again, at the time of this writing) who all want to learn more about the design to development process. I can say from personal experience, I owe a lot of my current skills to what I have learned from his videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has grown his channel into something much more than himself. At a certain point, you have people that are hungry for more and willing to support the content you make, and Travis has helped facilitate that. In return, he has created an online community group for the patrons of the show, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patreon.com/devtips&quot;&gt;which you can check out here on Patreon &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Community here is a group full of Designers and Developers across the globe that want to learn more and give their help towards making the web a better place. Here, I have found a dumptruck load full of people willing to help others with questions and problems they’re having with their current designs and code. Everyone here can be found around the YouTube comments and Patreon page. From here I’ve found work as a web designer with a startup and countless smaller projects to help me grow as a designer. You’ll find no better coding community than this to get feedback, play around with codepens and joke around about the industry. We’ve started hosting some weekly google hangouts for people in the group to showcase what you’ve learned or came up with that week.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/post-devtips/hangout.png&quot; alt=&quot;devtips community hangout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-megamaker&quot;&gt;What is MegaMaker?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;callout megamaker&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;It doesn't matter if you swing hammers, a keyboard and mouse, a paintbrush, a needle and thread, or a soldering iron. We're all makers here.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spearheaded by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mijustin&quot;&gt;Justin Jackson&lt;/a&gt;, a crazy Canadian who has a knack for creating awesome products. He started 2016 with a MegaMaker challenge. Justin still plans on &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/16gVonXDjdvlj6yBP-hOmbktugZ3-QkLOw_nhRN9xlUs/&quot;&gt;making 100 things in 2016&lt;/a&gt;. With a challenge like that he created a podcast to document his progress. Since then he’s created quite a following for his challenge with &lt;a href=&quot;http://megamaker.co/secret/&quot;&gt;a new secret society&lt;/a&gt; and new seasons of the MegaMaker podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin is a product centric creative that is helping other people learn how to make a living as an independent creator. He gives out plenty of tips for digital products and marketing tips. Recently he’s been challenging others with miniature maker missions to create something around a general topic. If you want to see how to make an interesting mark on today’s society, I really recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://megamaker.simplecast.fm/episodes/24177-life-is-better-when-you-make-stuff&quot;&gt;checking out his podcast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-seanwes&quot;&gt;What is Seanwes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;callout seanwes&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Grow your business and connect with people who won't let you quit.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sean McCabe and his team of awesome people have created a large network of awesome resources for people who are trying to build and sustain an audience driven business. Just recently he’s driven up the price of the community up to reflect the amount of value that you get from being a part of this network. &lt;a href=&quot;http://seanwes.com/&quot;&gt;I still recommend this&lt;/a&gt; if you are an entrepreneur that focuses on your audience to engage with and increase the success of your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The members in here challenge each other to grow and keep on top of their game with constant learning and discussions. Sean is working really hard at creating learning paths and other resources for current and future members of the community. Within the membership you get access to all of the seanwes podcasts in the vault as well as watching live streams of their podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a paid member to get some value from what their brand has, but there are also things like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://seanwes.com/conference/&quot;&gt;seanwes conference &lt;/a&gt;and his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/seanwestv&quot;&gt;seanwes.tv youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;. Don’t let the price of the membership scare you because practicing what he teaches pays for any expense you find in here. I believe he does this too so you take this as an investment towards your future and treat it seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-im-going-to-have-to-pay-if-i-want-to-take-part-of-any-of-this&quot;&gt;So I’m going to have to pay if I want to take part of any of this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, these are just the ones that I choose to spend and invest my time into. There are countless communities everywhere you look. Some other great ones to get into that I can also suggest are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.freecodecamp.com/&quot;&gt;The awesome people in the freeCodeCamp Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.freecodecamp.com/free-code-camp-now-has-local-groups-1e0b58bae363#.fxunadgff&quot;&gt;Any of their meetups&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/meetups&quot;&gt;Dribbble.com’s Meetups&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find a community for whatever you are interested in to help you grow. You might think that you don’t have time for engaging within these but you make time for the things that are important to you. Maybe people there are helping keep you aligned with a public commitment you’ve made for yourself or your brand, or maybe you’re touching base with a coach or mentor. Maybe you’re helping coach and mentor another person. Maybe you have been spending years going in the wrong direction with your current path because you’ve never gotten feedback on what you’re doing. Everyone there is going to help keep you away from that and cares about your success. All because you’re part of their own community too. This is all an investment of your time, you get out of the community what you put into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;look-for-ways-to-engage-in-a-community-for-your-interests-and-see-how-that-helps-you-grow&quot;&gt;Look for ways to engage in a community for your interests and see how that helps you grow!&lt;/h3&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Here we unpackage why engaging in communities is important for developers and designers, especially for those starting out a an entrepreneur. Along with going over what the different communities like Seanwes and the DevTips Community have to offer and why they’re a gold mine for new creatives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">keySpark Branding Redesign</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/07/17/keySpark-brand-redesign/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="keySpark Branding Redesign" /><published>2016-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/07/17/keySpark-brand-redesign</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/07/17/keySpark-brand-redesign/"></content><category term="case-study" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Burn the Boats: An Update On My Current 2016 Goals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/07/13/Update-On-2016-Goals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Burn the Boats&amp;#58; An Update On My Current 2016 Goals" /><published>2016-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/07/13/Update-On-2016-Goals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/07/13/Update-On-2016-Goals/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;burn-the-boats-a-brutal-but-fitting-metaphor&quot;&gt;Burn the boats… a brutal but fitting metaphor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I love about phrases like these is that though they are removed from any part of what we do now in our time, their message is reused and &lt;em&gt;repurposed&lt;/em&gt; into something that fits our current situations. I am not the only person to have thought moving forward means we need to burn our boats and bridges.
I faced a tough decision a year ago, a tough one that would have afforded my family a little more wiggle room in our budget or sent us down a spiral of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-did-i-start-why-am-i-doing-this&quot;&gt;Where did I start, why am I doing this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July of 2015, my son had just turned a month old, my family was sliding backwards phenomenally each month into debt, and I was stagnant and unhappy in my position at work. There was an opportunity at my work to apply for a promotion. &lt;em&gt;Yeah, Darian, promotions happen a lot when you work at a bank&lt;/em&gt;. But not for the branch I had been working at. Being there three years and all would have some merit into getting hired on as a higher position in the company, so I chose to apply for it. What I found was that I had more seniority over getting to choose when I wanted to go to lunch or take my vacation than I did with what promotions I was able to get. What they cared about was how much business I brought to the bank based on extra products or services I could vaguely recommend and hope to god they bite. I won’t go into everything but the way my mindset was about that situation was different than what the bank wanted me to do. I didn’t always agree that some things were best for the customer. I was in a vulnerable position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do I do? I applied for the better position anyways. After a while of playing that game of interviews and it was revealed that I wouldn’t get the position, my eyes turned elsewhere. My goal, to find something that I can enjoy doing that helps a lot of people and still allows me to spend time with my love and our son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deus-ex-machina&quot;&gt;Deus ex Machina&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a tough criteria for something that doesn’t sound like a standard 40hr job, a unicorn job that I could be chasing for years. Maybe I could do call center work, or maybe that would be me doing non profit stuff. I turned my heads to the online job search engines and found something that fit the bill. It was the role of a marketing assistant and I knew that was something that I wanted. It would require updating and maintaining a website for a company, their branding, and any other search engine optimization things that the lead marketer would deem necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally applied. Took a refresher course on HTML and CSS using &lt;a href=&quot;http://codecademy.com&quot;&gt;CodeCademy&lt;/a&gt;, and went through those interviews as well. I even played the LinkedIn game where you find their hiring manager and get their attention… after a while they chose someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-many-cross-roads-so-little-time&quot;&gt;So many cross roads… So little time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../assets/goals.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;a watch counting down the time I have left&quot; /&gt;
After that luck ran out, I had a lot of thinking to do. I can either keep looking for conventional jobs or choose to do something else. I spent a good time researching my criteria for jobs that allow me to do what I wanted to be able to do and applied to about 30-35 jobs, about 8 which called back for interviews. I wasn’t sure what my goals were but I knew that I needed more and more information in about making websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed now with the idea that I know HTML and CSS &lt;em&gt;since I just took a refresher course of some language I learned for a month in high school&lt;/em&gt;, why wouldn’t I think now that the world is at my fingertips. I looked into web development and what it would take to get a job in tech. There were a lot of hoops but the goal was to provide for my family…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the next two months would have gone by, there was a period of time in October — November where I didn’t have much time with my commitments to learn code. But I found a 3 month long technical course and decided to jump into it. It cost a lot of money, but that money was an investment to get us a little better off. I was able to better understand what was in my learning path and where I needed to put focus to be effective. I started to realize the more I learned, the less I knew. I had to choose if this was the route that I was going to take my family down. The boats had to be burned. My focus at work would be split from now on, one eye on keeping my job’s requirements satisfied, and the other ahead to what projects, people, communities, and activities would bring me forward in my career &lt;a href=&quot;https://darianrosebrook.com/article/handling-expectational-debt-and-falling-behind&quot;&gt;which I have talked about before.&lt;/a&gt;. This was the point I realized I needed something more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-a-community-of-the-most-helpful-people-in-the-world&quot;&gt;Enter a community of the most helpful people in the world&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously. I didn’t think I needed to be around other people who had skills for making websites, &lt;em&gt;they’re just competition to what I’m trying to do anyways&lt;/em&gt;. I didn’t realize the full value of what I was missing out on until I ran across the YouTube show &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtube.com/devtipsfordesigners&quot;&gt;devtips&lt;/a&gt;. I joined hastily and have since loved being part of that DevTips community. Any time that I am stuck I have somebody there who is willing to try a hand at what I’m doing, as well as I have the opportunity to help others learn and grow too. I embedded myself in that and the books I was reading to help get my skills to par. I was recommended some great books that are both centered around design and development. I was recommended podcasts and case studies. Everything that helped put me into the position I am in now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a few months later I was recruited onto a wonderful team of developers as the lead designer to help them with an agency website. I will still have the freedom to work on any projects I take on for myself, but for now I am excited for the possibilities that are coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now confident in my ability for creating websites and designs to take on more clients and deliver custom solutions to the goals their brands and business take. .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-my-goal&quot;&gt;What is my goal?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2016, I had sat down and had a conversation with a few people and came up with a circle of friends who decided to make goals for the year. I hadn’t done this in many years myself but with each person came a challenging task for each.
I thought mine looked pretty reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/2016-objectives.jpg &quot; alt=&quot;my 2016 goals&quot; class=&quot;float cf&quot; /&gt;
I want to help other people out and their businesses by offering my services as a designer and developer to achieve their goals. I want to be able to teach what I know as efficiently and widespread as I know how, helping others who have similar interests do the same. I wanted to be able to provide for my family in a way that allows me to be around when they need me to be and watch their hearts grow. I’ve started burning my boat and am stepping onto shore of a grand possibility. People say that it isn’t as glamourous as everything said. I disagree. This is what I love to do. I want to eventually turn this into a larger organization of designers and get them on board, but for now, my one man show is going to be enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started here with this goal of getting everything on this list done just before the year’s end. I can say I’m about halfway there. I have half of the full stack completed for freeCodeCamp, started learning Ruby, I have gotten a job as a remote worker doing front end design and branding, as well as opened up for freelancing. I have half of my branding projects done as well as half of my portfolio site branded and finished. The only thing I need to work on is the projects, the freelance clients and putting some savings away to switch over to design full time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to set foot on the same path, you can checkout a fellow developer’s post &lt;a href=&quot;http://christopherpound.com/so-you-want-to-be-a-web-developer&quot;&gt;on how to become a web developer&lt;/a&gt; for a good learning path. And for design, a great resource would be &lt;a href=&quot;http://hackdesign.org&quot;&gt;hackdesign.org&lt;/a&gt; for some great resources on learning design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a while to get used to working this hard. I’ve literally spent as much time as a full time job learning and getting my skills up to par. I work 40hrs a week at work and an extra 25 - 35 hours at home on design. As soon as there’s enough income to step into it full time. &lt;em&gt;It’s game on, baby….&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Burn the boats… a brutal but fitting metaphor
What I love about phrases like these is that though they are removed from any part of what we do now in our time, their message is reused and repurposed into something that fits our current situations. I am not the only person to have thought moving forward means we need to burn our boats and bridges.
I faced a tough decision a year ago, a tough one that would have afforded my family a little more wiggle room in our budget or sent us down a spiral of uncertainty.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grow Your Code Logo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/05/22/grow-your-code/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grow Your Code Logo" /><published>2016-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/05/22/grow-your-code</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/05/22/grow-your-code/"></content><category term="case-study" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Out- Branding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/05/21/out-branding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Out- Branding" /><published>2016-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/05/21/out-branding</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/case-study/2016/05/21/out-branding/"></content><category term="case-study" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Handling Expectational Debt And Falling Behind.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/20/handling-expectational-debt-and-falling-behind/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Handling Expectational Debt And Falling Behind." /><published>2016-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/20/handling-expectational-debt-and-falling-behind</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/20/handling-expectational-debt-and-falling-behind/">&lt;p&gt;Why are we all given the same 24 hours? A lot of people seem to get more done than I can, and yet no one has more time during the day than others. Even since I started working 6 years ago, I have not earned any extra time in my life. Why do I feel more exhausted than my earlier self? I believe it has to do with the amount of expectational debt that I have found myself in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is a commodity. It is both finite and infinite. We only have 24 hours to use and it does not replenish until the following day. We have to protect our use of that time just as much as we protect the use of our money. When we say yes and commit to things, we are spending some of the expectations held for that day. So when you overspend your time on those expectations, it is akin to blowing apart your spending budget. &lt;em&gt;You get into debt from your expectations.&lt;/em&gt; You have to be mindful about the areas you choose to spend your hours. So if you don’t have enough time, it’s because you already spent that time on something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-found-myself-falling-behind&quot;&gt;How I found myself falling behind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/600/1*WjvFA3wtFd0FvpDoqFsyJg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The stagnant problem&quot; class=&quot;float cf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I carry a lot of responsibility. I am a father, I am a lover, and I am the main provider of my household. My time is spent trying to improve the quality of my family’s life and our relationships. And by working on that, my time has been spread pretty thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love my family more than anything in the world. They are a big factor in why I do what I do. So it is no surprise that I am willing to do what I can for us to make a living. I had to say no to a lot of things over the past year. That meant putting my skateboard on the shelf, my music on hold, and I put drawing on the back–burner. I spent my sole focus on working at the bank for 40 hours a week and in my business another 15. But with all of that effort were still falling behind financially. So I decided it was time to pursue a different path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After realizing halfway through the previous year that we were going south financially every month, I chose to start pursuing a different career. I’m developing myself as a designer. I haven’t designed anything since 2009, so I had to go get some education on the subject. This meant fitting in education into a schedule that I was already working 55 hours a week in and trying to maintain my family life. Let me run my schedule by you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wake up at 4:50 AM to take care of hygiene.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I work on designing things for a portfolio until 7:30 AM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I go to work at the bank from 8:30 AM to 6 PM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Come home to spend time with family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~ 10 PM to 12 AM I alternate days doing business or homework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day. (except Sunday and Tuesday: that is my family time)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems manageable. It looks like all of the steps are there. So why is it I feel exhausted? Why is it I keep falling behind?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout&quot;&gt; &lt;h2&gt; You have to put the big rocks in first, say no to some fine sand.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/rocks-hands.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The big rock goes first&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That schedule is manageable if I don’t do anything outside of that list. But somewhere in there is my family’s time, driving to and from work, building my personal brand, keeping my portfolio projects going, keeping up on my public and personal commitments, eating — It is an exhaustive list that keeps me exhausted too. The spare change (or the fine sand) has to be put towards the things that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is what you’re doing right now going to impact where you’ll be 3 — 5 years from now? I heard this question a little while ago, only recently have I started to act on it. Because I started putting small things in front of the big ones, I have started to fall behind on my commitment to building my personal brand. I caught myself watching unnecessary amounts of YouTube videos and reading unnecessary articles that aren’t really getting me anywhere towards my goals. It can feel like having fourteen dollars left and choosing it to spend on cheeseburgers instead of gasoline for your car. So I had to redefine what it is I want to be, and how it was I was going to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started taking charge of the time I spend, cutting those unnecessary things out and re-purposing that time towards building my family’s quality of life. I choose my commitments carefully now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ZfWeFbSv0xE_ym4N1kFsvQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The Solution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you catch yourself falling behind, you have to define a successful day as &lt;em&gt;showing up and doing good work&lt;/em&gt;. Did you stay true to the commitments that you have? For me, showing up is posting a piece that helps define my personal brand every day. It’s a tall commitment, but it’s necessary. It is going to work and meeting that damn quota every day. It’s about coming home and spending that much needed quality time that I get with Sara and Atlas. I show up and I do good work towards the big things in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am designing my life to be fulfilling and productive at the same time. I started taking inventory of my time and found that about 5 hours of my time was being used up by the unnecessary things in life. So I nixed a lot of the areas in my life where time seemed to vanish. I started to say no to a bunch of those things. My current routine is designed to build up my brand as a designer until that can replace my main source of income. Until more breathing room in my day comes available, my time will be spent on the things that matter; on the things that will help my family 3–5 years down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-will-your-life-improve-by-cutting-out-the-unnecessary-and-unproductive-things&quot;&gt;How will your life improve by cutting out the unnecessary and unproductive things?&lt;/h3&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Why are we all given the same 24 hours? A lot of people seem to get more done than I can, and yet no one has more time during the day than others. Even since I started working 6 years ago, I have not earned any extra time in my life. Why do I feel more exhausted than my earlier self? I believe it has to do with the amount of expectational debt that I have found myself in.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Work Flow Process for Creating Better Websites</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/12/Web-Design-Work-Flow-for-2016/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Work Flow Process for Creating Better Websites" /><published>2016-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/12/Web-Design-Work-Flow-for-2016</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/12/Web-Design-Work-Flow-for-2016/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-design-is-so-much-more-than-layout-and-fonts&quot;&gt;Web design is so much more than layout and fonts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing websites is so much more than throwing together some layout and fonts. The process dives much deeper than that. What web design has become is an iterative process of discovery and problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your brand has a goal in mind and I want to help that goal be realized through design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-process&quot;&gt;My process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask a list of questions to understand the brand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Establish a proposal based off of questionnaire and content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start Research and Development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilize my process of quality assurance to ensure the design is the best solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give a great presentation on the work and decisions and handing over the keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions-are-the-building-blocks-and-the-center-of-focus-on-doing-a-site-design&quot;&gt;Questions are the building blocks and the center of focus on doing a site design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to understand the scope of the project. Utilizing a process of asking solid, fact finding questions will help us get to the core of what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are the expert of what you do and who you do it for. My job is to get to know that part of your brand and apply that to the goals we have laid out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;What role does a website have in your brand goals?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-is-king&quot;&gt;Content is King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any of my work to be effective, I need to know what content will be designed. It’s like building a very nice shelf, it looks great, but if we put stuff on it, is it going to fit? &lt;em&gt;Will there be enough space? Will there be too much space? Maybe what we needed was a storage compartment?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visitors to your site should feel like they know where things are, and can complete the tasks they are there to accomplish, without having to think about it. After we itemize what content is there, we can consider going into the &lt;em&gt;R &amp;amp; D&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;well-establish-a-proposal-and-agreement-for-the-project&quot;&gt;We’ll establish a proposal and agreement for the project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have established goals and have discovered what the value of reaching those goals would bring to your brand and organization, I put together a proposal that restates the goals and desired solution that outlines how I will help you achieve them through design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also put together an agreement that will have a project specific process, initial timeline guides, and terms for the business relationship. We will have set aside time to go over this, paragraph by paragraph so that we can be sure we are on the same page before moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;r--d-initialization--this-is-where-the-magic-happens&quot;&gt;R &amp;amp; D: Initialization — This is where the magic happens&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stage of the process goes over the hardest part of web design: solving the problems. I do my best work here when I have a pen and sketchbook close by.
I grab a good cup of coffee, some good tunes, and I start going over the initial questionnaire. &lt;em&gt;What styles would best describe this brand’s message?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll pull in some raw resources that compliment the styles and brand and go into full designer mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes doing some research on what is current in your industry can help, sometimes going out into the world and finding a nice spot to iterate ideas will work too. But the main point is getting some initial ideas of where the design should be going. This leads into designing a great style-guide for your content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;r--d-ideation-and-creation&quot;&gt;R &amp;amp; D: Ideation and Creation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wireframes will be created from the collection of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Style guides&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raw materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobile, Tablet, and Desktop wireframes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Site maps and story boards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creation process will go through targeted revisions and tweaks that allow me to come up with the best solution towards your project goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve noticed there isn’t a revision process with the client, understand that I pride myself on the professional work that I do. By hiring me for doing design work, you are allowing me to use my expertise as an expert of my field, much as I respect you as an expert of your field. Therefore, you are most equipped to describe your goals and provide content for the design, and I am most equipped to take those goals and content and use my design skills, expertise, and insight to build a solution that will accomplish your goals. This takes a large deal of trust from both parties, but it will allow me to come to the best solution for the outlined goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;r--d-prototyping-and-development&quot;&gt;R &amp;amp; D: Prototyping and Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will then be baked in the oven at 350 degrees for 18 minutes until crispy and golden brown. Not, really, but it will be coded and tested thoroughly across browsers and devices. What code bases and functionality is determined from the questionnaire and creation phases. A thorough consult with an SEO expert is always suggested, but the site will start to be outfitted with current SEO best practices out of the gate. After numerous hours of development, some quality assurance will be conducted to ensure that every stone hasn’t been left unturned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;well-meet-for-a-presentation-and-hand-over-the-keys&quot;&gt;We’ll meet for a presentation and hand over the keys&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now you must realize that each part of this process will be well documented and formatted for presentation. I keep detailed notes on every design decision and understand that for someone to follow why a decision was placed to help your brand actualize your project goals. We’ll meet for presenting the new site and it’s documentation. We’ll talk about the challenges and the solutions, as well as any things that went exceptionally well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the presentation, and having collected the final payment, everything is delivered to you with any necessary directions for use. A ‘handing over of keys,’ so to speak. We’ll migrate any and all designed content into your possession. From here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-is-time-to-show-your-new-looks&quot;&gt;It is time to show your new looks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s like getting a new haircut and storing pictures of the last one. We’ll blast the new look for the next few days about the new look and archive the old one. We’ll submit the new site or the new changes to the search engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-all-of-this-youre-still-here&quot;&gt;After all of this, you’re still here&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that means unless you’re a designer looking up another process to glean from, you and I really need to connect and talk about doing some great work together. A brand’s project to me is an investment in that brand’s future. I hope you treat that the same way.
(p.s. if you’re a designer or developer as well, I’d love to hear from you too. Shoot me a message and I’ll read it too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;stop-markdown from indenting buttons&quot;&gt;&lt;button data-href=&quot;#form&quot; type=&quot;button&quot; name=&quot;button&quot; class=&quot;contactBtn primary btn&quot;&gt;Hire Me&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Web design is so much more than layout and fonts</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Branding and Logo Design Work Flow for 2016</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/01/Branding-and-Logo-Design-Work-Flow-for-2016/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Branding and Logo Design Work Flow for 2016" /><published>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/01/Branding-and-Logo-Design-Work%20Flow-for-2016</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/05/01/Branding-and-Logo-Design-Work-Flow-for-2016/"></content><category term="article" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>
