<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-09T14:11:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Portfolio</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Creating a custom membership site</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/compass-community-2-0" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating a custom membership site" /><published>2018-03-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/compass-community-2-0</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/compass-community-2-0">&lt;p&gt;A little while ago I teased to a few members of my design community that I’m building something special for them in the background. I have a lot of things that I’ve been building lately, but I plan for this to be the end-all be-all replacement for the slack group we’re in.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="updates" /><summary type="html">A little while ago I teased to a few members of my design community that I’m building something special for them in the background. I have a lot of things that I’ve been building lately, but I plan for this to be the end-all be-all replacement for the slack group we’re in.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An interview by Chris Green of This Design Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/design-interview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An interview by Chris Green of This Design Life" /><published>2018-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/design-interview</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/design-interview">&lt;p&gt;I got a chance to talk to Chris Green of This Design Life about what I do with Compass and what he’s building with &lt;a href=&quot;https://thisdesignlife.net&quot;&gt;This Design Life&lt;/a&gt;. After some talking he took some time to interview me which you can see at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thisdesignlife.net/darian-rosebrook-interview/&quot;&gt;this interview page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="updates" /><summary type="html">I got a chance to talk to Chris Green of This Design Life about what I do with Compass and what he’s building with This Design Life. After some talking he took some time to interview me which you can see at this interview page</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meetup with Juan Valera from Coastalco.co</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/meetup-with-juan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meetup with Juan Valera from Coastalco.co" /><published>2018-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/meetup-with-juan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/meetup-with-juan">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I run is a design community for people who are looking to increase their skills as a designer. This week, I was able to meet up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/justcallmejuan&quot;&gt;Juan Valera&lt;/a&gt; from the design agency &lt;a href=&quot;https://coastalco.co&quot;&gt;Coastal&lt;/a&gt;. He runs this agency full time and is in the product design space for the medical industry. Definitely go &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmps.co/redesigning-twistle&quot;&gt;check out the work he did on this case study for Twistle&lt;/a&gt;. Juan is a member of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://compassofdesign.com/community&quot;&gt;Compass of Design Commmunity&lt;/a&gt; so it was good to finally meet up after talking over the last 2 years online.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="updates" /><summary type="html">One of the things that I run is a design community for people who are looking to increase their skills as a designer. This week, I was able to meet up with Juan Valera from the design agency Coastal. He runs this agency full time and is in the product design space for the medical industry. Definitely go check out the work he did on this case study for Twistle. Juan is a member of the Compass of Design Commmunity so it was good to finally meet up after talking over the last 2 years online.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I got invited to AMAfeed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/design-ama" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I got invited to AMAfeed" /><published>2018-03-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/design-ama</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/design-ama">&lt;p&gt;Hey if you have a moment, you should check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://freelanceama.amafeed.com/ama-about-running-a-design-business-on-the-side-of-a-full-time-job-my-name-is-488950&quot;&gt;this Ask Me Anything thread that I started over on AMAfeed.com&lt;/a&gt;. Here I go over exactly what I’m doing with trying to run a day job on the side of a business. Or is this vice versa? IDK, I’m running both at the same time. If you have time, throw in some questions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="updates" /><summary type="html">Hey if you have a moment, you should check out this Ask Me Anything thread that I started over on AMAfeed.com. Here I go over exactly what I’m doing with trying to run a day job on the side of a business. Or is this vice versa? IDK, I’m running both at the same time. If you have time, throw in some questions!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Manuel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/manuel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manuel" /><published>2018-01-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/manuel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/manuel">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MKDesignzManuel&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-twitter&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/MkDesignzManuel&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-globe&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Twitter | twitter</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I just completed two years of moonlighting as a freelance designer.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/year-in-review-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I just completed two years of moonlighting as a freelance designer." /><published>2017-12-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/year-in-review-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/year-in-review-2">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/1*Ela67mPWfErWNS2B_5c1fQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/darianrosebrook&quot;&gt;A fraction of everything that I posted in 2017 on
Dribbble.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-just-completed-two-years-of-moonlighting-as-a-freelance-designer&quot;&gt;I just completed two years of moonlighting as a freelance designer.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-what-building-two-design-focused-businesses-at-the-same-time-looks-like&quot;&gt;And what building two design focused businesses at the same time looks like.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago in this first week of December, I started learning to code
websites. I had my eyes set on becoming a freelance web designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glam and glory was appealing, meaning that I was able to do something that
interested me (finally) and get paid handsomely to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This path has set me on one of the best and trying journeys of my life. Along
the way I have met new and interesting people. I’ve failed at a handful of
things that opened it’s way to new things or trying again from different angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve built and perfected processes that make building two businesses at the same
time less stressful than it was starting out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/year-zero-my-journey-as-a-designer-a172342e3ee3&quot;&gt;That story has been told in my first year’s year-end
review&lt;/a&gt;,
geared towards helping new people to the web design industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2017-was-a-good-year&quot;&gt;2017 was a good year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-it-was-the-most-challenging-of-them-all&quot;&gt;But it was the most challenging of them all&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been able to accomplish so much, yet not enough. It’s felt fulfilling,
yet severely lacking. And I’ve been growing a lot, all while standing still.
I’ve been making money as a designer, but I’m not quite where I need to be to
sustain all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-talk&quot;&gt;Let’s talk.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*VhoE7JmWYNvFZpxEaaVM3A.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-year-started-out-great-too&quot;&gt;This year started out great too.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a long sit down at the end of 2016 after spending nearly all of my free
time working months on the redesign of an enormous web app as the only designer
on the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project left me with time in order to focus on continuing my learning of
design, no time to build my business on the side while working with KeySpark and
my full time job, no time for my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I had to really consider if now was the right time for me to become a web
designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are trying to build your business on the side of having 2 day jobs (A
bank teller and a web designer for a remote dev agency) you start to have scope
creep, but for your obligations in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were to survive, I would need to focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;that-was-this-year-focus&quot;&gt;That was this year. Focus.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a sit down talk with a friend who had been a designer for years before
starting her family, she had mentioned to me that there are more things to
design than just websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She had me audit what I was doing, where I was spending most of my time, where
my heart was at with everything, and then imagine myself if I went that
direction for the next 15–20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was that line of work going to satisfy my urge to create? Could I keep up with
the rapid growth and iteration of the design world? What if what I’m good at
designing isn’t hot anymore? Do I have the ability to change? Do I have the
skills right now to be creating timeless designs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hard questions got me to audit what I was doing and what my true goals
were with being a designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*XE_gitQYI7AuP3TrgqLCVA.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;The Plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like I had suddenly started to see what I wanted to do in life. It’s a
really weird and fulfilling thing when you have the pieces of what you do and
who you’re best equipped to help cross each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-had-two-goals&quot;&gt;I had two goals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve my professional process to move into the premium market of designers,
building out the foundation to start a branding design agency focused on helping
businesses transition from a small mom-and-pop into something more professional
or corporate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a platform to help designers who can’t afford design school (or want to
teach themselves) learn how to effectively build their skills, market themselves
better, becoming a better professional in the process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-coach&quot;&gt;The Coach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in December of 2016, my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://justinjackson.ca&quot;&gt;Justin Jackson
&lt;/a&gt;had been opening up slots in his mentorship coaching
group he was starting. This group was a run of four months of personalized
coaching, goal setting, group Q&amp;amp;A events, and progress checking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kickstarted my year with some heavy goals and ambitions that I knew I had
the ability to finish. But Justin, seeing what I planned to do, knew that I
would be burning myself out if I hadn’t fixed my current work situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was exhausted all the time, working my butt off for a ~$17,500 take home
income along with working a second job that was barely paying anything better
than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was going to be focusing on growing my business, I had to make sure my day
job income was taking care of my base costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had I relied on my side income to pay bills, I would have damaged my passion to
do this venture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your side-hustle, when starting out, is like a sapling. If you try to lean up
against it, it’s going to snap like a twig and become crushed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have the business where it can support your current lifestyle without
the use of you business income, along with a solid foundation (months of income
saved in the bank) and a steady stream to nurture it, you are able to leave the
day job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was currently using too much of that side income and needed to cut to bare
necessities and focus on increasing my income on both fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great-minds-think-better-together&quot;&gt;Great minds think better together&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the coaching started, we formed an online mastermind meetup where the
people who were in the coaching sessions would meetup on a video hangout every
week to share progress and gain feedback on our projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people in the group were mainly developers who each had some sort of SaaS
Product (software as a service) or product they were selling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goals this year was to make a sustainable living on the things we love to
do, and build out new ideas to test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was working on all the things that resulted from my coaching sessions with
Justin, this group was a way to keep myself more accountable to the goals, along
side that I was paying a lot of money in order to have access to the things I
was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advice and feedback from both sides of this coin (Mentorship and Mastermind)
was exactly what I needed to give me the motivation to build out and test the
feasibility of my ideas and fed each other into what naturally happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-design-business-split-into-two-sides-of-the-same-coin&quot;&gt;My design business split into two sides of the same coin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These businesses feed each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of them does branding design engagements with clients&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other shares the experiences, knowledge, and fosters growth around becoming
a more professional designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-do-they-feed-into-each-other&quot;&gt;How do they feed into each other?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://compassofdesign.com&quot;&gt;Compass of design&lt;/a&gt;, I had to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;design the logo and build a branding design system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build the site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;design a branded email template&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;design branded title cards for the newsletters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build and design custom tools for the site to be used&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create automation campaigns, sales funnels, and track analytics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;branded products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;social media profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://somagnetic.com&quot;&gt;So Magnetic&lt;/a&gt; I needed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn to build a more professional process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn to position myself with high value design clients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn to price on value to the client rather than arbitrary rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn how to fit heavy hitting projects in my currently overloaded schedule&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rebranding-the-newsletter&quot;&gt;Rebranding the newsletter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have a lot of thoughts, ideas, and experiences locked inside of your head
and most of them will die with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— Sean McCabe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This newsletter isn’t something that I wanted to do solely for myself. Plenty of
people could benefit hearing from someone who is in the fight, working on
creating a design business from the ground up, learning about design along the
way and then turning around and teaching what he’s learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path to becoming a designer is also very hazy and not well documented
outside of the college/design school setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to be able to be a guide to show these people who are eager to learn,
but lost without an idea of where to go. I wanted to create the compass that
guides them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This turned into changing my focus on writing about Designing with Confidence,
to me helping people find the direction they needed to go to level up their
design skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(Yeah the newsletter was originally called Designing with Confidence)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for me to teach design to others, I had to become a perpetual design
student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will always be something to add on a topic, because even if someone else
has written about it, done a talk on it, created that theory before, there’s no
new ideas out in the world any more. Just a fresh perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that running my design newsletter has been the quickest and most
efficient way for me to learn design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the newsletter grew, so did the position of the brand. Ideally, the brand is
a way to help empower other designers with the skills they need to defeat
impostor syndrome and start designing with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New things were added every week to this brand until it became it’s own full
standalone thing, all seated within it’s parent brand** So Magnetic.**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-compass-of-design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://compasofdesign.com&quot;&gt;The Compass of Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a certain point, I had several people who were on the newsletter that had
started asking questions about the other people on the newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the other people struggling with?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What types of designers are on this list?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Am I the only one who has problems with this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions had got me thinking that I was hitting close to the right spot
with the positioning of my newsletter. But someone can only get so far on the
thoughts and insight of one person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided in April to open up the newsletter list and start a private slack
community for the people who signed up for the newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-community&quot;&gt;The Community&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group started growing very slowly for the first few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally I was sending invites to anyone who joined the newsletter. The amount
of accepted invites compared to the actual signups were about 1 signup to every
4 or 5 that joined the newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a certain point (and I can’t remember when) I added a little checkbox that
said “also, send me a Compass of Design Community invite” which worked better so
that I was only sending invites to those who wanted it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then again that only worked a little bit better.&lt;br /&gt; By the time we got to
50 people in the community, I had started dealing with a few really negative
people that made it into the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a group I built to foster growth and I ended up having to talk to a few
members individually, I had to kick one person out of the group, another left of
his own accord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that got me thinking of the value that you get being for being a community
member. This thing is meant to help foster the growth of your skills and help
you become a better designer overall faster. All while building friendships,
acquaintances, skills, getting valuable feedback on work you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to close open registration for the community back in August, and new
members were only added if they messaged me personally asking to get in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did something soon after. I started charging new members for community
membership. This did 2 things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something that is open to everyone is open to both the good and the bad people.
By charging for community membership, I was able to help improve the quality by
challenging people to be serious about wanting to become a better designer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The increase in income from membership helps me focus exclusively on helping
these people grow and continue to invest back into them. Makes me want to invest
things like giving free goods, free course material, all sorts of stuff. It
improves the quality of the community membership on both fronts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this article, the community has grown to almost 75 people. All of you in
there are founding members of something great to come. I hope you all continue
to participate and grow together over the next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-products&quot;&gt;The Products&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Products like the design resources will continue to be added as they come
available. I plan on finishing the other two on the list soon and I hope to
continue to add as many resources as people need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-coaching&quot;&gt;The Coaching&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have plans for two courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing yourself as a designer&lt;/strong&gt; (50% built out)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designing with Confidence: The founding principles of design&lt;/strong&gt; (25% built)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also plan on expanding on a few of the topics of 2017 in video form on
YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll open up myself for private mentoring and coaching sessions through my
personal site where people can sign up to get specific and specially tailored
feedback and goals directly from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan on trying to get some small gigs teaching what I know in workshops both
online and in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is so much in store for the Compass of Design and community as the brand
continues to grow. You’ll see my goals at the end of the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rebranding-my-design-business&quot;&gt;Rebranding my design business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant that along with changing the position of my design newsletter, in
order to reach a higher market of design clients, I had to increase my
professionalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positioning was key, so in order to level up with my design business, I had to
start reverse engineering what a successful branding agency has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;qualities-of-an-agency-afloat&quot;&gt;Qualities of an agency afloat&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Excellent communication skills between the client and designer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A higher level of design skills than where I am right now.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ability to uncover goals, expectations and price based on goals and expected
value of the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ability to employ design strategy through a consistent professional process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being selective with taking on clients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extreme confidence and backing of choices made&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A large body of work that compliments and assures clients they’re making the
right choice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effective case studies that entice, explain, and convert visitors to start new
projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A clear and direct niche&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An excellent brand positioning statement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am nowhere near finishing all of the things on this list. But, with what I
have completed, I have become a much better designer and business person through
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing what I can to position my brand here in a niche market&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;But even then it’s insanely hard to pick a positioning statement. So why not use
all of them? &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yeah that hasn’t been quite as effective as I would have liked it to be. haha&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-target-market&quot;&gt;The Target Market&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-services&quot;&gt;The Services&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-change-in-professionalism&quot;&gt;The Change in Professionalism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year has been great for becoming a better professional. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-process&quot;&gt;The Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-have-i-learned&quot;&gt;What have I learned?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;special-thanks-in-no-particular-order&quot;&gt;Special thanks, in no particular order:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(and this is not a complete list, I promise there’s so much more I’ve learned
form each of you. These are just some of the biggest)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sara Weishaar&lt;/strong&gt; — For giving me grace and patience as I continue to build this
for us these next few years. You, my beautiful fiance, and our beautiful
children continue to inspire me to be a better man to support you all. I love
you and do this for you first and foremost. Even if sometimes you’re frustrated
that I’m working a lot, that ends soon and we’ll put these past few trying years
behind us. I love you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Justin Jackson&lt;/strong&gt; — for kicking my ass into gear this year to build things and
consistently auditing where I’m at and where I need to go in order to bridge
that gap. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://megamaker.co&quot;&gt;MegaMaker&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://justinjackson.ca&quot;&gt;JustinJackson.ca&lt;/a&gt;, MegaMaker Club)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Matt Bertino **— Your insight and building of&lt;a href=&quot;http://mailsnail.io&quot;&gt; Mail
Snail&lt;/a&gt; has been great to see what iterative changes and
perseverance can do with incoming revenue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Dan Coverdale **— For helping me understand the joys an follies of designing
products as a business (especially across the pond). Your neo-retro aesthetic is
always refreshing to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mike Eppel&lt;/strong&gt; — I don’t think I ever want to try to make a plugin at all
anymore. :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Michael Newman **— Thank you for all your insight with helping shape my ideas
to build out Compass of Design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sara Wood&lt;/strong&gt; — Even though our interactions were brief, I’ve learned a lot from
what you’ve shared this year&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Dan Pererra and Amy Parker **— Our small comments back and forth around your
project of visualizing the Red Sox Scores has been an interesting way to learn
about abstract data visualization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jonathan Friesen&lt;/strong&gt;—You were the first person to buy a product from me this
year. Thanks! Also, your adventures with projects, travel, and tenacity in life
have been really inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jordan Faux&lt;/strong&gt; — My friend that inspired me to become a designer and learn
illustrator. Though I might have outrun you initially, I’m always there to help
you get caught right back up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Michael Weibel **— Michael finished the 100 Daily UI challenge this year.
Every piece he’s shared on Dribbble and twitter has been epic and it’s been
great seeing someone’s skills build incrementally over time. If you’re ever
state-side, you have a friend here in Washington State! Maybe some day I’ll make
it over there too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Emily Ellis **— Thank you for being a part of the community. I’ve learned a
bit this year helping answer questions and giving feedback on your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sean McCabe **— I’ve been in the **seanwes&lt;/strong&gt; community since March 2016, and I
have yet to be disappointed by the access to valuable, quality content he and
his team produces. It’s a standard set for what I plan on putting out in the
world for Compass of Design. Very much appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Kyle Adams **— You helped me become a better writer this year, find the best
process on picking colors for design to date, and continue to inspire and
support my work. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Joelene Weeks **— It’s been great getting to know you. You and I have a lot of
parallels when we talk. I would hope to continue helping you grow with UX design
and help you while you build out your portfolio. (:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyrel Chambers&lt;/strong&gt; — Thanks for the opportunity to work with KeySpark this year
and help me perfect my client process for So Magnetic. Your continued support
and friendship has been one of the most valuable things to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Juliane Bone&lt;/strong&gt; — You have such a brilliant mind when it comes to branding
solutions. I’m always impressed too by your work and voracious appetite to learn
about becoming a great branding expert. You inspire me to grow each time with
those great questions you ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skip Jones&lt;/strong&gt; — You were one of the first 5 people that started the Compass of
Design community. I appreciate all the support and the resources that you’ve
given that helped shape my venture here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manuel Osorio&lt;/strong&gt; — I’m always interested in the projects you are working on in
your education classes. I’m glad that a lot of what I shared with Compass that
you’ve been able to apply so much!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ross Litzenberger&lt;/strong&gt; — Ross, you’ve been a tremendous help and valuable friend
when it comes to having questions about Git, RoR and just being a good friend,
and texting me to check in. I think you’re the only one who does and I always
appreciate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steve Morris&lt;/strong&gt; — Steve! Your comments on Dribbble have always been good
motivation to keep going. I’m always impressed with your line work, you have an
aesthetic that is simple, but difficult to do right. I think you’ve been really
growing your skills this year and I’m looking forward to seeing how you grow
next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amy Kotas&lt;/strong&gt; — Thank you for all your insights with running a side business
with a family. Sometimes just seeing you hustle as hard as I do has been enough
to help me keep this up. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ben Kochavy&lt;/strong&gt; — I’ve ran into so many people you’ve associated with this year
that I’m beginning to think we should become better friends. lol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Katie Wood&lt;/strong&gt; — Thanks for challenging me to think of things within the
community and constantly sharing good design resources. I hope that you continue
to grow your skills with design and your Heart &amp;amp; Sola Venture (:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peter D. Kaizer&lt;/strong&gt; — I don’t know of anyone who’s shared my articles more than
you. Thank you, friend. Your support is appreciated and know that I’m always
here to answer questions should you have them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrew Krause&lt;/strong&gt; — Also among the first 5 of the community members and a
friend. You build things so quickly that I get jealous sometimes and motivated
to find better ways to automate things. You got an interesting brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spencer Fry&lt;/strong&gt; — I’ve had a lot of fun getting to know you and the things
you’re excited for to help your community with Podia. As a customer, I
appreciate your human interaction and level of support. I aspire to have the
dedication you have to your audience. Thanks for all the support (customer and
personal)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brian Hollingsworth&lt;/strong&gt; — I get to see someone who’s a few steps ahead of me
building his design practice in real time. I’ve taken many notes on the things
you do and share and I must say that you inspire me to be more vocal about how
branding and design impacts business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joe Busch&lt;/strong&gt; — You’ve got such an interesting future ahead of you. I hope you
get a lot out of being around other designers this year, and I look forward to
seeing your work grow. You’ve got the talent, now let’s build those skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jonathan Holt&lt;/strong&gt; — Youv’e liked nearly every single Dribbble shot I’ve put out
and you’re not a bot. So that got a mention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Akna Marquez&lt;/strong&gt; — I get inspired by anybody who does a different field of
design than I do. Reading your articles and being on your newsletter help me
understand more about design from angles I never thought about. The
conversations we’ve had were insightful and glad to know that we’re all working
on figuring out where we want to be with clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Rogie King and Justin Mezzell **— I made pins and stickers for the community
and it’s inspired by the fact that you guys work so hard to put out quality
crap. I want to put out quality crap like you guys. Keep jiving!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Meg Robichaud, Meg Lewis and Laura Bohill, Helen Tran, Dina Rodriguez, Deidre
Olsen **— All of these people have helped me understand a lot of what women deal
with. It’s been insightful and helped me think of how I act as a man and audit
myself for how, when, and what to do to help women be uplifted instead of
hindered in society. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you’re reading this and weren’t mentioned, don’t think I don’t care about
you. These are some of the biggest things I’ve learned this year (and can
remember right now as I’m building this article) If you and I have interacted at
all in the last year, know that I appreciate you and you are worth a lot to me.
Don’t for a second think that I discount you or our interactions (:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-vision-for-next-year&quot;&gt;My vision for next year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For next year, I want to be able to finally retire the dayjob.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who does know me knows that I usually go to bed around 10 or 11pm and
wake up around 4 am to get working on my design business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That has to stop. I can only do this for so long until my body gives out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;next-year-i-plan-on-10x-ing-my-design-business&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next year I plan on 10x-ing my design business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting my case studies onto my website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leveraging referrals and outbound marketing efforts as well as inbound marketing
efforts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building up a cash reserve that equates to 6 or more months of all expenses at
my current lifestyle level&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building up a cash flow to sustain that cash reserve or blow it to bigger
proportions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pricing on value rather than time or flat fee (that means not over charging my
clients, and not undercharging myself)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;next-year-i-plan-on-10x-ing-the-value-behind-compass-of-design-community&quot;&gt;Next year I plan on 10x-ing the value behind Compass of Design Community&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Membership making it a better investment for new members (and current ones)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sending out free stuff like stickers, pins, and digital goods to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://compassofdesign.com/community&quot;&gt;members of
the community&lt;/a&gt; (still deciding on
semi-annually or quarterly.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finishing the Designer’s Self Assessment Tool’s second version to include a much
better learning path that is custom tailored to a person’s level of experience
and chosen design discipline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start doing more things like live events and group challenges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explore what the platform can become and start the vision of what version 2.0 of
the community looks like and how to grandfather what ever group exists into that
new version&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue to do the things that drive the most value to members of the audience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make many new friends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so excited for where this is going. I hope that you’ll all come with me and
work on your projects like I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank you for everything you as an audience has given me in support.
Without it, this would be a very dull adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*mo7_gcoDhIhJHCOLPxMfLg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;as-a-designer-have-you-got-your-sklls-ready-for-next-year-in-2018&quot;&gt;As a designer, have you got your sklls ready for next year in 2018?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of
their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week we go over ways to market yourself better by improving your design
skills, your personal brand, and other topics to further develop as a great
designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tap either picture to get started investing in your design skills (:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;Tap on either picture to get started at compassofdesign.com&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="article" /><summary type="html">A fraction of everything that I posted in 2017 on Dribbble.com I just completed two years of moonlighting as a freelance designer. And what building two design focused businesses at the same time looks like. Two years ago in this first week of December, I started learning to code websites. I had my eyes set on becoming a freelance web designer. The glam and glory was appealing, meaning that I was able to do something that interested me (finally) and get paid handsomely to do so. This path has set me on one of the best and trying journeys of my life. Along the way I have met new and interesting people. I’ve failed at a handful of things that opened it’s way to new things or trying again from different angles. I’ve built and perfected processes that make building two businesses at the same time less stressful than it was starting out. That story has been told in my first year’s year-end review, geared towards helping new people to the web design industry. 2017 was a good year But it was the most challenging of them all I have been able to accomplish so much, yet not enough. It’s felt fulfilling, yet severely lacking. And I’ve been growing a lot, all while standing still. I’ve been making money as a designer, but I’m not quite where I need to be to sustain all this. Let’s talk. This year started out great too. I had a long sit down at the end of 2016 after spending nearly all of my free time working months on the redesign of an enormous web app as the only designer on the project. This project left me with time in order to focus on continuing my learning of design, no time to build my business on the side while working with KeySpark and my full time job, no time for my family. And I had to really consider if now was the right time for me to become a web designer. When you are trying to build your business on the side of having 2 day jobs (A bank teller and a web designer for a remote dev agency) you start to have scope creep, but for your obligations in life. If I were to survive, I would need to focus. That was this year. Focus. After a sit down talk with a friend who had been a designer for years before starting her family, she had mentioned to me that there are more things to design than just websites. She had me audit what I was doing, where I was spending most of my time, where my heart was at with everything, and then imagine myself if I went that direction for the next 15–20 years. Was that line of work going to satisfy my urge to create? Could I keep up with the rapid growth and iteration of the design world? What if what I’m good at designing isn’t hot anymore? Do I have the ability to change? Do I have the skills right now to be creating timeless designs? These hard questions got me to audit what I was doing and what my true goals were with being a designer. The Plan It’s like I had suddenly started to see what I wanted to do in life. It’s a really weird and fulfilling thing when you have the pieces of what you do and who you’re best equipped to help cross each other. I had two goals Improve my professional process to move into the premium market of designers, building out the foundation to start a branding design agency focused on helping businesses transition from a small mom-and-pop into something more professional or corporate. Build a platform to help designers who can’t afford design school (or want to teach themselves) learn how to effectively build their skills, market themselves better, becoming a better professional in the process. The Coach Back in December of 2016, my friend Justin Jackson had been opening up slots in his mentorship coaching group he was starting. This group was a run of four months of personalized coaching, goal setting, group Q&amp;amp;A events, and progress checking. This kickstarted my year with some heavy goals and ambitions that I knew I had the ability to finish. But Justin, seeing what I planned to do, knew that I would be burning myself out if I hadn’t fixed my current work situation. I was exhausted all the time, working my butt off for a ~$17,500 take home income along with working a second job that was barely paying anything better than that. If I was going to be focusing on growing my business, I had to make sure my day job income was taking care of my base costs. Had I relied on my side income to pay bills, I would have damaged my passion to do this venture. Your side-hustle, when starting out, is like a sapling. If you try to lean up against it, it’s going to snap like a twig and become crushed. When you have the business where it can support your current lifestyle without the use of you business income, along with a solid foundation (months of income saved in the bank) and a steady stream to nurture it, you are able to leave the day job. I was currently using too much of that side income and needed to cut to bare necessities and focus on increasing my income on both fronts. Great minds think better together After the coaching started, we formed an online mastermind meetup where the people who were in the coaching sessions would meetup on a video hangout every week to share progress and gain feedback on our projects. The people in the group were mainly developers who each had some sort of SaaS Product (software as a service) or product they were selling. Our goals this year was to make a sustainable living on the things we love to do, and build out new ideas to test. As I was working on all the things that resulted from my coaching sessions with Justin, this group was a way to keep myself more accountable to the goals, along side that I was paying a lot of money in order to have access to the things I was doing. The advice and feedback from both sides of this coin (Mentorship and Mastermind) was exactly what I needed to give me the motivation to build out and test the feasibility of my ideas and fed each other into what naturally happened. My design business split into two sides of the same coin These businesses feed each other. One of them does branding design engagements with clients The other shares the experiences, knowledge, and fosters growth around becoming a more professional designer. How do they feed into each other? In order to build Compass of design, I had to: design the logo and build a branding design system build the site design a branded email template design branded title cards for the newsletters build and design custom tools for the site to be used create automation campaigns, sales funnels, and track analytics branded products social media profiles In order to build So Magnetic I needed to: learn to build a more professional process learn to position myself with high value design clients learn to price on value to the client rather than arbitrary rates learn how to fit heavy hitting projects in my currently overloaded schedule Rebranding the newsletter You have a lot of thoughts, ideas, and experiences locked inside of your head and most of them will die with you. — Sean McCabe This newsletter isn’t something that I wanted to do solely for myself. Plenty of people could benefit hearing from someone who is in the fight, working on creating a design business from the ground up, learning about design along the way and then turning around and teaching what he’s learned. The path to becoming a designer is also very hazy and not well documented outside of the college/design school setting. I wanted to be able to be a guide to show these people who are eager to learn, but lost without an idea of where to go. I wanted to create the compass that guides them. This turned into changing my focus on writing about Designing with Confidence, to me helping people find the direction they needed to go to level up their design skills. (Yeah the newsletter was originally called Designing with Confidence) In order for me to teach design to others, I had to become a perpetual design student. There will always be something to add on a topic, because even if someone else has written about it, done a talk on it, created that theory before, there’s no new ideas out in the world any more. Just a fresh perspective. I would say that running my design newsletter has been the quickest and most efficient way for me to learn design. As the newsletter grew, so did the position of the brand. Ideally, the brand is a way to help empower other designers with the skills they need to defeat impostor syndrome and start designing with confidence. New things were added every week to this brand until it became it’s own full standalone thing, all seated within it’s parent brand** So Magnetic.** The Compass of Design At a certain point, I had several people who were on the newsletter that had started asking questions about the other people on the newsletter. Questions like: What are the other people struggling with? What types of designers are on this list? Am I the only one who has problems with this? These questions had got me thinking that I was hitting close to the right spot with the positioning of my newsletter. But someone can only get so far on the thoughts and insight of one person. So I decided in April to open up the newsletter list and start a private slack community for the people who signed up for the newsletter. The Community The group started growing very slowly for the first few months. Originally I was sending invites to anyone who joined the newsletter. The amount of accepted invites compared to the actual signups were about 1 signup to every 4 or 5 that joined the newsletter. At a certain point (and I can’t remember when) I added a little checkbox that said “also, send me a Compass of Design Community invite” which worked better so that I was only sending invites to those who wanted it. But then again that only worked a little bit better. By the time we got to 50 people in the community, I had started dealing with a few really negative people that made it into the community. This was a group I built to foster growth and I ended up having to talk to a few members individually, I had to kick one person out of the group, another left of his own accord. And that got me thinking of the value that you get being for being a community member. This thing is meant to help foster the growth of your skills and help you become a better designer overall faster. All while building friendships, acquaintances, skills, getting valuable feedback on work you’re doing. I decided to close open registration for the community back in August, and new members were only added if they messaged me personally asking to get in. I did something soon after. I started charging new members for community membership. This did 2 things. Something that is open to everyone is open to both the good and the bad people. By charging for community membership, I was able to help improve the quality by challenging people to be serious about wanting to become a better designer. The increase in income from membership helps me focus exclusively on helping these people grow and continue to invest back into them. Makes me want to invest things like giving free goods, free course material, all sorts of stuff. It improves the quality of the community membership on both fronts. As of this article, the community has grown to almost 75 people. All of you in there are founding members of something great to come. I hope you all continue to participate and grow together over the next year. The Products Products like the design resources will continue to be added as they come available. I plan on finishing the other two on the list soon and I hope to continue to add as many resources as people need. The Coaching I have plans for two courses. Marketing yourself as a designer (50% built out) Designing with Confidence: The founding principles of design (25% built) I also plan on expanding on a few of the topics of 2017 in video form on YouTube. I’ll open up myself for private mentoring and coaching sessions through my personal site where people can sign up to get specific and specially tailored feedback and goals directly from me. I plan on trying to get some small gigs teaching what I know in workshops both online and in person. There is so much in store for the Compass of Design and community as the brand continues to grow. You’ll see my goals at the end of the post. Rebranding my design business This meant that along with changing the position of my design newsletter, in order to reach a higher market of design clients, I had to increase my professionalism. Positioning was key, so in order to level up with my design business, I had to start reverse engineering what a successful branding agency has. Qualities of an agency afloat Excellent communication skills between the client and designer A higher level of design skills than where I am right now. The ability to uncover goals, expectations and price based on goals and expected value of the project The ability to employ design strategy through a consistent professional process Being selective with taking on clients Extreme confidence and backing of choices made A large body of work that compliments and assures clients they’re making the right choice Effective case studies that entice, explain, and convert visitors to start new projects A clear and direct niche An excellent brand positioning statement I am nowhere near finishing all of the things on this list. But, with what I have completed, I have become a much better designer and business person through it. I’ve been doing what I can to position my brand here in a niche market But even then it’s insanely hard to pick a positioning statement. So why not use all of them? Yeah that hasn’t been quite as effective as I would have liked it to be. haha The Target Market The Services The Change in Professionalism This year has been great for becoming a better professional. The Process What have I learned? Special thanks, in no particular order: (and this is not a complete list, I promise there’s so much more I’ve learned form each of you. These are just some of the biggest) Sara Weishaar — For giving me grace and patience as I continue to build this for us these next few years. You, my beautiful fiance, and our beautiful children continue to inspire me to be a better man to support you all. I love you and do this for you first and foremost. Even if sometimes you’re frustrated that I’m working a lot, that ends soon and we’ll put these past few trying years behind us. I love you. Justin Jackson — for kicking my ass into gear this year to build things and consistently auditing where I’m at and where I need to go in order to bridge that gap. (MegaMaker, JustinJackson.ca, MegaMaker Club) **Matt Bertino **— Your insight and building of Mail Snail has been great to see what iterative changes and perseverance can do with incoming revenue **Dan Coverdale **— For helping me understand the joys an follies of designing products as a business (especially across the pond). Your neo-retro aesthetic is always refreshing to see. Mike Eppel — I don’t think I ever want to try to make a plugin at all anymore. :P **Michael Newman **— Thank you for all your insight with helping shape my ideas to build out Compass of Design. Sara Wood — Even though our interactions were brief, I’ve learned a lot from what you’ve shared this year **Dan Pererra and Amy Parker **— Our small comments back and forth around your project of visualizing the Red Sox Scores has been an interesting way to learn about abstract data visualization Jonathan Friesen—You were the first person to buy a product from me this year. Thanks! Also, your adventures with projects, travel, and tenacity in life have been really inspiring. Jordan Faux — My friend that inspired me to become a designer and learn illustrator. Though I might have outrun you initially, I’m always there to help you get caught right back up. **Michael Weibel **— Michael finished the 100 Daily UI challenge this year. Every piece he’s shared on Dribbble and twitter has been epic and it’s been great seeing someone’s skills build incrementally over time. If you’re ever state-side, you have a friend here in Washington State! Maybe some day I’ll make it over there too. **Emily Ellis **— Thank you for being a part of the community. I’ve learned a bit this year helping answer questions and giving feedback on your work. Sean McCabe **— I’ve been in the **seanwes community since March 2016, and I have yet to be disappointed by the access to valuable, quality content he and his team produces. It’s a standard set for what I plan on putting out in the world for Compass of Design. Very much appreciated. **Kyle Adams **— You helped me become a better writer this year, find the best process on picking colors for design to date, and continue to inspire and support my work. Thank you. **Joelene Weeks **— It’s been great getting to know you. You and I have a lot of parallels when we talk. I would hope to continue helping you grow with UX design and help you while you build out your portfolio. (: Tyrel Chambers — Thanks for the opportunity to work with KeySpark this year and help me perfect my client process for So Magnetic. Your continued support and friendship has been one of the most valuable things to me. Juliane Bone — You have such a brilliant mind when it comes to branding solutions. I’m always impressed too by your work and voracious appetite to learn about becoming a great branding expert. You inspire me to grow each time with those great questions you ask. Skip Jones — You were one of the first 5 people that started the Compass of Design community. I appreciate all the support and the resources that you’ve given that helped shape my venture here. Manuel Osorio — I’m always interested in the projects you are working on in your education classes. I’m glad that a lot of what I shared with Compass that you’ve been able to apply so much! Ross Litzenberger — Ross, you’ve been a tremendous help and valuable friend when it comes to having questions about Git, RoR and just being a good friend, and texting me to check in. I think you’re the only one who does and I always appreciate that. Steve Morris — Steve! Your comments on Dribbble have always been good motivation to keep going. I’m always impressed with your line work, you have an aesthetic that is simple, but difficult to do right. I think you’ve been really growing your skills this year and I’m looking forward to seeing how you grow next year. Amy Kotas — Thank you for all your insights with running a side business with a family. Sometimes just seeing you hustle as hard as I do has been enough to help me keep this up. Thank you. Ben Kochavy — I’ve ran into so many people you’ve associated with this year that I’m beginning to think we should become better friends. lol Katie Wood — Thanks for challenging me to think of things within the community and constantly sharing good design resources. I hope that you continue to grow your skills with design and your Heart &amp;amp; Sola Venture (: Peter D. Kaizer — I don’t know of anyone who’s shared my articles more than you. Thank you, friend. Your support is appreciated and know that I’m always here to answer questions should you have them. Andrew Krause — Also among the first 5 of the community members and a friend. You build things so quickly that I get jealous sometimes and motivated to find better ways to automate things. You got an interesting brain. Spencer Fry — I’ve had a lot of fun getting to know you and the things you’re excited for to help your community with Podia. As a customer, I appreciate your human interaction and level of support. I aspire to have the dedication you have to your audience. Thanks for all the support (customer and personal)! Brian Hollingsworth — I get to see someone who’s a few steps ahead of me building his design practice in real time. I’ve taken many notes on the things you do and share and I must say that you inspire me to be more vocal about how branding and design impacts business. Joe Busch — You’ve got such an interesting future ahead of you. I hope you get a lot out of being around other designers this year, and I look forward to seeing your work grow. You’ve got the talent, now let’s build those skills. Jonathan Holt — Youv’e liked nearly every single Dribbble shot I’ve put out and you’re not a bot. So that got a mention. Akna Marquez — I get inspired by anybody who does a different field of design than I do. Reading your articles and being on your newsletter help me understand more about design from angles I never thought about. The conversations we’ve had were insightful and glad to know that we’re all working on figuring out where we want to be with clients. **Rogie King and Justin Mezzell **— I made pins and stickers for the community and it’s inspired by the fact that you guys work so hard to put out quality crap. I want to put out quality crap like you guys. Keep jiving! **Meg Robichaud, Meg Lewis and Laura Bohill, Helen Tran, Dina Rodriguez, Deidre Olsen **— All of these people have helped me understand a lot of what women deal with. It’s been insightful and helped me think of how I act as a man and audit myself for how, when, and what to do to help women be uplifted instead of hindered in society. Thank you. If you’re reading this and weren’t mentioned, don’t think I don’t care about you. These are some of the biggest things I’ve learned this year (and can remember right now as I’m building this article) If you and I have interacted at all in the last year, know that I appreciate you and you are worth a lot to me. Don’t for a second think that I discount you or our interactions (: My vision for next year For next year, I want to be able to finally retire the dayjob. Anyone who does know me knows that I usually go to bed around 10 or 11pm and wake up around 4 am to get working on my design business. That has to stop. I can only do this for so long until my body gives out. Next year I plan on 10x-ing my design business This will mean: Getting my case studies onto my website Leveraging referrals and outbound marketing efforts as well as inbound marketing efforts Building up a cash reserve that equates to 6 or more months of all expenses at my current lifestyle level Building up a cash flow to sustain that cash reserve or blow it to bigger proportions Pricing on value rather than time or flat fee (that means not over charging my clients, and not undercharging myself) Next year I plan on 10x-ing the value behind Compass of Design Community Membership making it a better investment for new members (and current ones) This will mean: Sending out free stuff like stickers, pins, and digital goods to the members of the community (still deciding on semi-annually or quarterly.) Finishing the Designer’s Self Assessment Tool’s second version to include a much better learning path that is custom tailored to a person’s level of experience and chosen design discipline Start doing more things like live events and group challenges Explore what the platform can become and start the vision of what version 2.0 of the community looks like and how to grandfather what ever group exists into that new version Continue to do the things that drive the most value to members of the audience Make many new friends I am so excited for where this is going. I hope that you’ll all come with me and work on your projects like I am. I want to thank you for everything you as an audience has given me in support. Without it, this would be a very dull adventure. As a designer, have you got your sklls ready for next year in 2018? Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of their craft. Every week we go over ways to market yourself better by improving your design skills, your personal brand, and other topics to further develop as a great designer. Tap either picture to get started investing in your design skills (: Tap on either picture to get started at compassofdesign.com</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designer Crimes of the 21st Century</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/designer-crimes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designer Crimes of the 21st Century" /><published>2017-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/designer-crimes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/designer-crimes">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/0*ArKZMhpaum02M8_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;designer-crimes-of-the-21st-century&quot;&gt;Designer Crimes of the 21st Century&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;please-take-this-advice-even-if-it-is-comic-sans-p&quot;&gt;Please take this advice, even if it is Comic Sans :P&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has definitely been a fun year, growing our design community and creating a
lot of new articles to share around&lt;a href=&quot;https://compassofdesign.com/archive/writing&quot;&gt; design principles and design
thinking&lt;/a&gt;. I know that sometimes
these written pieces can get long, but this one won’t be too bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually mainly images (which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/sh/1sxjgegrwvst5m3/AAD4mXZWvARn9vscGBddMlk5a?dl=0&quot;&gt;you can download from my dropbox if you
want&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did intentionally design these this way as an example of what not to do. Which
could get annoying. Let’s see. 😂&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we continue to improve our design skills, we train our eye to notice really
good design. One side effect however, we tend to not look for the things where
we might be creating bad designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these things I mention below &lt;strong&gt;I have been or sometimes still am guilty
of.&lt;/strong&gt; Even now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just happens that eventually you learn to avoid these mistakes with time,
practice, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/what-is-the-fastest-way-to-learn-something-3f64297089ef&quot;&gt;dedication to getting
better&lt;/a&gt;
(which includes seeking feedback on your work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not everyone is as fine tuned as they should be, especially when it
comes to their B.S. Meter for over glorified design. So in case you haven’t seen
them, here’s some design crimes that should be avoided at all costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*0f7wUf2PXC_7cpd0.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stealing-someone-elses-design-or-aesthetic&quot;&gt;Stealing someone else’s design or aesthetic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways that we borrow styles from others. It’s okay to start
designing within a new style. This is fine, and sometimes refreshing… However…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the time what we call “Getting Design Inspiration ” or “Research” is
actually going to Dribbble and copying something that looks like what you want
your work to look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t try to pass off someone’s own work or aesthetic as your own. Don’t
ride off the coattails of someone else’s success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only thing that can save you here is by documenting process. Have something
that shows how you got from idea to execution and you might just be in the
clear. ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*X5wDNI6LmfDkmzjD.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;splitting-articles-between-pages&quot;&gt;Splitting articles between pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that some websites use this to increase the number of advertisements some
people are exposed to, but don’t do this because there’s no reason a block of
text can’t be rendered on a webpage or screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hampers the experience someone has when going to your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to make sure someone reads all the way through, consider different
methods of breaking up an article to keep people engaged, rather than
frustrating them with a barrage of ads and load times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*IfbSg1kD-AFBOos-.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-having-enough-contrast&quot;&gt;Not having enough contrast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to make sure you have enough contrast between colors.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://contrastchecker.com/&quot;&gt;contrastchecker.com/&lt;/a&gt; is a good resource for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a stark change in contrast between colors, you’re causing unnecessary
stress on someone’s brain trying to pull the two elements apart in their head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure that something passes the “Squint” test where you squint your eyes. If
you can still see it, it’s good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-clip-art-past-2007&quot;&gt;Using clip art past 2007&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many other options you can use besides clip art. Even a stick
figure drawing would be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the new art within mobile apps like Snapchat, Instagram, Facebook, iOS,
etc. These are actually sometimes well designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about going into Microsoft word, or online to get “Free graphics.”
for a design you’re working on. What is usually free lacks quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-keeping-user-experience-consistent-across-devices&quot;&gt;Not keeping user experience consistent across devices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t cut out features of your site just because there are smaller screen sizes.
A lazy designer will skip trying to make something work correctly on the other
screen/devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone using something on their desktop browser would probably expect the same
level of experience on the mobile app or website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creating-too-much-eye&quot;&gt;Creating too much eye&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your design becomes too busy, the person looking at it will have to strain
their eyes, brains, and focus, trying to figure out what the heck is going on in
your design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-white-space&quot;&gt;No white space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is okay to have some white-space in your design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good design is not filling the space with everything you can, it’s showing
restraint by making the design with just as much as it needs to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-mobile-tap-targets-too-tiny&quot;&gt;Making mobile tap targets too tiny&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably tried to use a mobile app by clicking on something, only to have
to tap it multiple times until you actually get it. Same goes for using your
mouse… These action targets need to be easy to hit, and not bigger than they
need to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-too-much-of-the-same-photo&quot;&gt;Using too much of the same photo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I see a stock photo on one page, I better not click to another page and see
that same damn photo on that page too unless it’s relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the photo isn’t even appropriate for the content it is there to
compliment. Just make sure that each element has a purpose and that it is
relevant to what you are communicating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overusing-one-style-in-your-portfolio&quot;&gt;Overusing one style in your portfolio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this all the time. If you use only one style in your portfolio, a
potential employer will get a good idea of what you’ll produce for them, but
they won’t ever get to know what else you can do. Sometimes being able to branch
out will surprise you with what work you attract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I just used this same style above this crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slapping-a-golden-spiralratio-on-something-to-make-it-feel-designed&quot;&gt;Slapping a golden spiral/ratio on something to make it feel designed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t understand the method, spend some time learning as much as you can.
Don’t just do it because it’s trendy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-pure-white-or-pure-black&quot;&gt;Using pure white or pure black&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Not everything is so #000000 and #FFFFFF&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pure black and pure white are very jarring to the eyes. You can soften even a
little bit by choosing even 1% brighter/darker in their respective directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;any-crime-involving-mishandled-typography&quot;&gt;Any crime involving mishandled typography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not stretch type horizontally, do not kern the letters if you don’t
understand how to make it better, don’t use fonts that are different than the
tone you are going for, don’t stretch type vertically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typography is something that takes a while to learn, but even a basic knowledge
should help you avoid doing any of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sacrificing-the-usability-of-a-design-to-make-it-pretty&quot;&gt;Sacrificing the usability of a design to make it pretty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If what you’re doing aesthetically makes the design hard to use, consider why
you’re even doing that design in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with the goal of the project, not the aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-too-many-visual-tricks&quot;&gt;Using too many visual tricks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that KISS Principle? Keep It Simple, Stupid (KISS). The more things you
try to do with the design, the less satisfied you’ll be with it. Practice
restraint and you might have a cool design the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-clear-logic-to-the-hierarchy-or-grid-system&quot;&gt;No clear logic to the hierarchy or grid system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice layout and composition often. Pay attention to patterns you see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doing a layout yourself, even a simple grid or hierarchy structure will
keep your design in good shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-doing-enough-research-on-the-intended-audience&quot;&gt;Not doing enough research on the intended audience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of researching what someone had already designed for your target
audience, come up with research strategies that actually help you understand the
target demographic. Search the internet with research strategies for (whatever)
Design, and how to research your target market. You’ll find plenty of resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-using-high-enough-resolution-photography&quot;&gt;Not using high enough resolution photography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take note of the common sizes that someone is going to use your design. (Print,
Web Design, Mobile App Design, Video Game Design, Advertising, etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking that bit of time will help you find the right resolution for your
photography and keep your pictures from getting too pixelated or compressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forgetting-about-the-empty-states-edge-cases-or-any-use-case-for-that-matter&quot;&gt;Forgetting about the empty states, edge cases, or any use case for that matter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you considered what your design will look like if someone doesn’t fill in
the field?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my biggest projects I’ve worked on had way too many fields to fill in and
not one person used all of them in their profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;being-too-hot-headed-thinking-youve-learned-it-all-all-before-actually&quot;&gt;Being too hot headed, thinking you’ve learned it all (all before actually&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mastering your craft), trying to be seen as something you are not…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You only know as much as you’ve been exposed to. The world of design can’t be
learned in a year, or two, or ten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you have to be open to the fact that things change, new conventions,
methods, tools are created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the mindset of a perpetual student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s always something to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-you-ever-want-to-get-some-serious-design-practice-under-your-belt&quot;&gt;If you ever want to get some serious design practice under your belt…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of
their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week we go over ways to market yourself better, giving and getting design
feedback, improving your design professionalism, and other topics to further
develop your skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re currently accepting new members for the group and have big plans (and free
stuff) for 2018 coming real soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://compassofdesign.com/community&quot;&gt;Compass of Design&lt;/a&gt; to get
started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/1*mo7_gcoDhIhJHCOLPxMfLg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/design?source=post&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/design-thinking?source=post&quot;&gt;Design
Thinking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/ux?source=post&quot;&gt;UX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/ui?source=post&quot;&gt;UI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/web-design?source=post&quot;&gt;Web Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;darian-rosebrook&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/@darianrosebrook&quot;&gt;Darian Rosebrook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brand Identity Designer for  &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/itssomagnetic&quot;&gt;@itssomagnetic&lt;/a&gt;,
running a design community at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/compassofdesign&quot;&gt;@compassofdesign&lt;/a&gt;. I write to help others
grow their skills as designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;compass-of-design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/?source=footer_card&quot;&gt;Compass of Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design
Community to help you strengthen your skills in design, business/freelance, and
marketing yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, actually™&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am working for 10 years in Japan. One thing I have learned is that this
assumption while broadly correct, has some cultural sensitivity to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t speak for other CJK cultures, but it is certainly true at the very least
Japanese EC customers love high information density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with you, I do know most of different cultures are bound by certain
conventions like that. Thank you for the reminder. I’ll see if I can amend my
statement. (:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It still can’t hurt having a bit of breathing room for most other designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the insight, Philipp!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and I am still trying to add more white space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact though: in my last and my current company I have been working on
enterprise facing apps and here the situation is very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree, but this may change with the advent of OLED screens becoming the norm.
I find it awful in magazines designs too, but since OLED screens have better
colour reproduction (at the right viewing angle), many designers will want to
try those out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not looking forward to that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Designer Crimes of the 21st Century Please take this advice, even if it is Comic Sans :P It has definitely been a fun year, growing our design community and creating a lot of new articles to share around design principles and design thinking. I know that sometimes these written pieces can get long, but this one won’t be too bad. It’s actually mainly images (which you can download from my dropbox if you want). I did intentionally design these this way as an example of what not to do. Which could get annoying. Let’s see. 😂 As we continue to improve our design skills, we train our eye to notice really good design. One side effect however, we tend to not look for the things where we might be creating bad designs. Some of these things I mention below I have been or sometimes still am guilty of. Even now. It just happens that eventually you learn to avoid these mistakes with time, practice, and dedication to getting better (which includes seeking feedback on your work). However, not everyone is as fine tuned as they should be, especially when it comes to their B.S. Meter for over glorified design. So in case you haven’t seen them, here’s some design crimes that should be avoided at all costs. Stealing someone else’s design or aesthetic There are many ways that we borrow styles from others. It’s okay to start designing within a new style. This is fine, and sometimes refreshing… However… A lot of the time what we call “Getting Design Inspiration ” or “Research” is actually going to Dribbble and copying something that looks like what you want your work to look like. You shouldn’t try to pass off someone’s own work or aesthetic as your own. Don’t ride off the coattails of someone else’s success. The only thing that can save you here is by documenting process. Have something that shows how you got from idea to execution and you might just be in the clear. ;) Splitting articles between pages I know that some websites use this to increase the number of advertisements some people are exposed to, but don’t do this because there’s no reason a block of text can’t be rendered on a webpage or screen. It hampers the experience someone has when going to your site. In order to make sure someone reads all the way through, consider different methods of breaking up an article to keep people engaged, rather than frustrating them with a barrage of ads and load times. Not having enough contrast You need to make sure you have enough contrast between colors. contrastchecker.com/ is a good resource for that. Without a stark change in contrast between colors, you’re causing unnecessary stress on someone’s brain trying to pull the two elements apart in their head. Make sure that something passes the “Squint” test where you squint your eyes. If you can still see it, it’s good. Using clip art past 2007 There are so many other options you can use besides clip art. Even a stick figure drawing would be better. Some of the new art within mobile apps like Snapchat, Instagram, Facebook, iOS, etc. These are actually sometimes well designed. I’m talking about going into Microsoft word, or online to get “Free graphics.” for a design you’re working on. What is usually free lacks quality. Not keeping user experience consistent across devices Don’t cut out features of your site just because there are smaller screen sizes. A lazy designer will skip trying to make something work correctly on the other screen/devices. Someone using something on their desktop browser would probably expect the same level of experience on the mobile app or website. Creating too much eye If your design becomes too busy, the person looking at it will have to strain their eyes, brains, and focus, trying to figure out what the heck is going on in your design. Simple is better. No white space It is okay to have some white-space in your design. Good design is not filling the space with everything you can, it’s showing restraint by making the design with just as much as it needs to have. Making mobile tap targets too tiny You’ve probably tried to use a mobile app by clicking on something, only to have to tap it multiple times until you actually get it. Same goes for using your mouse… These action targets need to be easy to hit, and not bigger than they need to be. Using too much of the same photo When I see a stock photo on one page, I better not click to another page and see that same damn photo on that page too unless it’s relevant. Sometimes the photo isn’t even appropriate for the content it is there to compliment. Just make sure that each element has a purpose and that it is relevant to what you are communicating. Overusing one style in your portfolio I see this all the time. If you use only one style in your portfolio, a potential employer will get a good idea of what you’ll produce for them, but they won’t ever get to know what else you can do. Sometimes being able to branch out will surprise you with what work you attract. Also, I just used this same style above this crime. Slapping a golden spiral/ratio on something to make it feel designed If you don’t understand the method, spend some time learning as much as you can. Don’t just do it because it’s trendy. Using pure white or pure black Not everything is so #000000 and #FFFFFF Pure black and pure white are very jarring to the eyes. You can soften even a little bit by choosing even 1% brighter/darker in their respective directions. Any crime involving mishandled typography Do not stretch type horizontally, do not kern the letters if you don’t understand how to make it better, don’t use fonts that are different than the tone you are going for, don’t stretch type vertically. Typography is something that takes a while to learn, but even a basic knowledge should help you avoid doing any of those. Sacrificing the usability of a design to make it pretty If what you’re doing aesthetically makes the design hard to use, consider why you’re even doing that design in the first place. Start with the goal of the project, not the aesthetics. Using too many visual tricks Remember that KISS Principle? Keep It Simple, Stupid (KISS). The more things you try to do with the design, the less satisfied you’ll be with it. Practice restraint and you might have a cool design the first time. No clear logic to the hierarchy or grid system Practice layout and composition often. Pay attention to patterns you see. When doing a layout yourself, even a simple grid or hierarchy structure will keep your design in good shape. Not doing enough research on the intended audience Instead of researching what someone had already designed for your target audience, come up with research strategies that actually help you understand the target demographic. Search the internet with research strategies for (whatever) Design, and how to research your target market. You’ll find plenty of resources. Not using high enough resolution photography Take note of the common sizes that someone is going to use your design. (Print, Web Design, Mobile App Design, Video Game Design, Advertising, etc) Taking that bit of time will help you find the right resolution for your photography and keep your pictures from getting too pixelated or compressed. Forgetting about the empty states, edge cases, or any use case for that matter Have you considered what your design will look like if someone doesn’t fill in the field? One of my biggest projects I’ve worked on had way too many fields to fill in and not one person used all of them in their profile. Being too hot headed, thinking you’ve learned it all (all before actually mastering your craft), trying to be seen as something you are not… You only know as much as you’ve been exposed to. The world of design can’t be learned in a year, or two, or ten. But, you have to be open to the fact that things change, new conventions, methods, tools are created. Take the mindset of a perpetual student. There’s always something to learn. If you ever want to get some serious design practice under your belt… Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of their craft. Every week we go over ways to market yourself better, giving and getting design feedback, improving your design professionalism, and other topics to further develop your skills. We’re currently accepting new members for the group and have big plans (and free stuff) for 2018 coming real soon! Check out the Compass of Design to get started! Design Design Thinking UX UI Web Design By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out. Darian Rosebrook Brand Identity Designer for @itssomagnetic, running a design community at @compassofdesign. I write to help others grow their skills as designers. Compass of Design Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design Community to help you strengthen your skills in design, business/freelance, and marketing yourself. Well, actually™ I am working for 10 years in Japan. One thing I have learned is that this assumption while broadly correct, has some cultural sensitivity to it. I won’t speak for other CJK cultures, but it is certainly true at the very least Japanese EC customers love high information density. I agree with you, I do know most of different cultures are bound by certain conventions like that. Thank you for the reminder. I’ll see if I can amend my statement. (: It still can’t hurt having a bit of breathing room for most other designs. Thanks for the insight, Philipp! Thank you, and I am still trying to add more white space. Fun fact though: in my last and my current company I have been working on enterprise facing apps and here the situation is very different. I agree, but this may change with the advent of OLED screens becoming the norm. I find it awful in magazines designs too, but since OLED screens have better colour reproduction (at the right viewing angle), many designers will want to try those out. Not looking forward to that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stop getting stuck on your digital design concepts.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/sketching" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop getting stuck on your digital design concepts." /><published>2017-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/sketching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/sketching">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*FYln1kxn0OLaqXd0D-7xgQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;stop-getting-stuck-on-your-digital-design-concepts&quot;&gt;Stop getting stuck on your digital design concepts.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nothing-feels-better-than-finishing-a-design-quickly&quot;&gt;Nothing feels better than finishing a design quickly.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-beauty-of-speed&quot;&gt;The beauty of speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re anything like me, you are probably beating your head over whatever
design concept you’re working on in your design program right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m stuck on this piece and I’m probably never going to finish this design on
time”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, I am trying to finish a logo design or branding project with a lot going
on. There’s a certain project that I have been trying to finish, but I have very
little time during the day right now to do work. However, this project is
special. I wanted to make sure I had the opportunity to use my “more
professional” process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I forgot a crucial part of the design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sketching&quot;&gt;Sketching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sketching is vital to a project’s success.&lt;br /&gt; It gives you the ability to
iterate on ideas without the restriction of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dropdown Menus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Annoying vector handles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transparency and blend mode issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Color and gradient choices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Screens, battery life, wall plug ins…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blank screen hesitation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a bad habit of starting my designs directly on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;Yeah, those are my actual sketches. Not quite Instagram worthy, are they?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-beauty-of-iteration&quot;&gt;The beauty of iteration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-only-restraints-you-have-is-imagination&quot;&gt;The only restraints you have is imagination.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a person who has to work primarily with digital design programs to create
a finished product, I had a bad tendency to go straight to my design programs
and try to get a finished product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked a lot with Photoshop and it would take forever to get my layers fixed
and updated anytime I moved something. In Illustrator, I would have to reconnect
vector points, or re-crop something using Pathfinder tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that it’s possible to be very quick with using digital design tools like
this. Instead, what I’ve found about myself was: the process of &lt;strong&gt;using digital
tools takes much longer to come up with a great design&lt;/strong&gt; than if I had started
with a good ol’ pencil and paper combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was losing speed due to the rigidness of the design programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-need-to-focus-on-speed-of-iteration-and-that-comes-with-sketching-your&quot;&gt;**You need to focus on speed of iteration, and that comes with sketching your&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;designs first.**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-can-directly-compare-each-sketch-side-by-side-and-decide-what-to-tweak-with&quot;&gt;You can directly compare each sketch side by side and decide what to tweak with&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a simple eraser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you did this with your digital tools, it will take you a very long time to
master quick iteration. I get that you can drag, copy and paste, etc… but if you
rough shapes and do quick comparisons, you can get a good view of the different
ideas that work and those that don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put all of my sketches right next to each other and focus on delivering as
many bad ideas out of my head as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-can-quickly-get-all-the-bad-ideas-out-of-your-head&quot;&gt;You can quickly get all the “bad” ideas out of your head.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we think we have a really good idea in our head so when we jump to
digital first, we’ll spend a lot of time creating this idea and waste a lot of
time on something that was actually a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using the pen and paper, you can rapidly get as many ideas down on paper as
you can muster. This gives you a good overview of which ideas are good and which
ones you might want to skip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I use a ‘*’ for each one I want to keep, and an ‘x’ for each one I want to
discard.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t want to get married to a concept too early on in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-beauty-of-the-aha-moments&quot;&gt;The beauty of the “Aha!” moments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sometimes-you-end-up-with-the-best-direction-to-go-from-the-beginning&quot;&gt;Sometimes you end up with the best direction to go from the beginning.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was making another logo out of the number five and mountain peaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I usually create a logo, I have a long questionnaire that I use with the
client to get a good idea where to start. During this process of questions with
the client, I try to not think of anything relating to visuals until I
understand goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, even then, &lt;strong&gt;I might have a direction picked as soon as I start sketching&lt;/strong&gt;
that fits the brief perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, it’s simple to just hop over to the screens again and continue
refining the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This logo design was done in a day and accepted the next day. But if I had
started with the screen, I might not have had this idea as quickly as I did
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part is that I’m not limited by tools trying to get cutouts or offset
paths, building grids, etc. &lt;strong&gt;I’m just free sketching at this point.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An aha moment might come to you a lot easier if you are able to quickly scribble
out all the bad concepts first. It could take you 3 sketches, it could take you
303 sketches…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t know until you try this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-beauty-of-notes&quot;&gt;The beauty of notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking great notes during the sketching phase might be the easiest way to
improve a design once you take the design to digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have direct input to what is working well, what you might have to consider
when going to digital, possible layout/composition changes, explaining
interactions or “hard to sketch” ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In time, your ability to sketch will improve&lt;/strong&gt; along with your details in your
notes. You essentially give yourself immediate feedback on your concepts, which
you can then turn into &lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/writing-more-effective-case-studies-3dede1333c6a&quot;&gt;case study
material&lt;/a&gt;
at the end of the design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-can-also-get-valuable-feedback-from-others&quot;&gt;You can also get valuable feedback from others&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just take a quick picture and send it off to your design buddies in slack, your
client through email, your professor in college, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get feedback on your work and then take notes on what they respond with
directly on the sketches you’ve created. We do this a lot in the&lt;a href=&quot;https://compassofdesign.com/community&quot;&gt; Compass of
Design community&lt;/a&gt; in order to save time
staring at the same logo/website/branding package…etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notes will help you tremendously as you continue to go throughout the rest
of the design process. Saving time fiddling with tools or getting distracted by
other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-beauty-of-practice&quot;&gt;The beauty of practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-can-start-by-drawing-sticks-and-horrible-circles&quot;&gt;You can start by drawing sticks and horrible circles.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I give you full permission to suck&lt;/strong&gt; at sketching for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is to &lt;strong&gt;start and never stop doing it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more you sketch, the better your sketches become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more you focus on making your sketches as perfect as they could be, you’re
wasting the most precious thing you have in your design process. Time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your sketch doesn’t have to be perfect. You don’t even have to draw well.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m serious, not everyone’s sketches have to be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t quite get my sketches to that “&lt;strong&gt;viral shareability&lt;/strong&gt;” that some of
those Instagram artists/designers have. &lt;strong&gt;But what I can do is practice.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By sketching often (even for personal stuff, not just clients), I can learn to
generate more ideas quicker. &lt;strong&gt;This iterative approach helps me build the best
details on existing ideas.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not spending time trying to think of the keyboard shortcuts, or using the
color picker to find the best colors to start with, or finding the right actions
in the dropdown menus…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just spending time with good music thumping in the background creating
sketches with my pencil or pen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stuck-on-what-you-need-to-design&quot;&gt;Stuck on what you need to design?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Burn“ a page in your sketchbook with some warmup doodles. Start the habit of
sketching&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re going to benefit a lot by starting with your sketchbook first as long as
you keep it a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t think you have enough time, start small. Take 5 minutes before
starting your design to sketch out some quick ideas. After a while, you might be
able to completely create your [insert what ever type of design you do :P]
design using only a pencil and paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the transition from sketch to digital is just for cleaning up your concept
and presenting the end product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just start with the 5 minutes, build the habit of sketching from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*mo7_gcoDhIhJHCOLPxMfLg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-you-ever-want-to-get-some-serious-design-practice-under-your-belt&quot;&gt;If you ever want to get some serious design practice under your belt…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of
their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week we go over ways to market yourself better, giving and getting design
feedback, improving your design professionalism, and other topics to further
develop your skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Tap either picture **to get from where you are now to where you want to be. (:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;Tap on either picture to get started at compassofdesign.com&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/design?source=post&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/design-thinking?source=post&quot;&gt;Design
Thinking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/ux?source=post&quot;&gt;UX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/web-design?source=post&quot;&gt;Web Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/product-design?source=post&quot;&gt;Product
Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;darian-rosebrook&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/@darianrosebrook&quot;&gt;Darian Rosebrook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brand Identity Designer for  &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/itssomagnetic&quot;&gt;@itssomagnetic&lt;/a&gt;,
running a design community at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/compassofdesign&quot;&gt;@compassofdesign&lt;/a&gt;. I write to help others
grow their skills as designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;compass-of-design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/?source=footer_card&quot;&gt;Compass of Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design
Community to help you strengthen your skills in design, business/freelance, and
marketing yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Stop getting stuck on your digital design concepts. Nothing feels better than finishing a design quickly. The beauty of speed If you’re anything like me, you are probably beating your head over whatever design concept you’re working on in your design program right now. “I’m stuck on this piece and I’m probably never going to finish this design on time” Often, I am trying to finish a logo design or branding project with a lot going on. There’s a certain project that I have been trying to finish, but I have very little time during the day right now to do work. However, this project is special. I wanted to make sure I had the opportunity to use my “more professional” process. Unfortunately, I forgot a crucial part of the design process. Sketching Sketching is vital to a project’s success. It gives you the ability to iterate on ideas without the restriction of: Dropdown Menus Annoying vector handles Transparency and blend mode issues Color and gradient choices Screens, battery life, wall plug ins… Blank screen hesitation I had a bad habit of starting my designs directly on the screen. Let’s talk about that. Yeah, those are my actual sketches. Not quite Instagram worthy, are they? The beauty of iteration The only restraints you have is imagination. Being a person who has to work primarily with digital design programs to create a finished product, I had a bad tendency to go straight to my design programs and try to get a finished product. I worked a lot with Photoshop and it would take forever to get my layers fixed and updated anytime I moved something. In Illustrator, I would have to reconnect vector points, or re-crop something using Pathfinder tools. I know that it’s possible to be very quick with using digital design tools like this. Instead, what I’ve found about myself was: the process of using digital tools takes much longer to come up with a great design than if I had started with a good ol’ pencil and paper combination. I was losing speed due to the rigidness of the design programs. **You need to focus on speed of iteration, and that comes with sketching your designs first.** You can directly compare each sketch side by side and decide what to tweak with a simple eraser. If you did this with your digital tools, it will take you a very long time to master quick iteration. I get that you can drag, copy and paste, etc… but if you rough shapes and do quick comparisons, you can get a good view of the different ideas that work and those that don’t. I put all of my sketches right next to each other and focus on delivering as many bad ideas out of my head as possible. You can quickly get all the “bad” ideas out of your head. Sometimes we think we have a really good idea in our head so when we jump to digital first, we’ll spend a lot of time creating this idea and waste a lot of time on something that was actually a bad idea. By using the pen and paper, you can rapidly get as many ideas down on paper as you can muster. This gives you a good overview of which ideas are good and which ones you might want to skip. (I use a ‘*’ for each one I want to keep, and an ‘x’ for each one I want to discard.) You don’t want to get married to a concept too early on in the process. The beauty of the “Aha!” moments Sometimes you end up with the best direction to go from the beginning. I was making another logo out of the number five and mountain peaks. When I usually create a logo, I have a long questionnaire that I use with the client to get a good idea where to start. During this process of questions with the client, I try to not think of anything relating to visuals until I understand goals. But, even then, I might have a direction picked as soon as I start sketching that fits the brief perfectly. From there, it’s simple to just hop over to the screens again and continue refining the concept. This logo design was done in a day and accepted the next day. But if I had started with the screen, I might not have had this idea as quickly as I did here. The best part is that I’m not limited by tools trying to get cutouts or offset paths, building grids, etc. I’m just free sketching at this point. An aha moment might come to you a lot easier if you are able to quickly scribble out all the bad concepts first. It could take you 3 sketches, it could take you 303 sketches… You don’t know until you try this. The beauty of notes Taking great notes during the sketching phase might be the easiest way to improve a design once you take the design to digital. You have direct input to what is working well, what you might have to consider when going to digital, possible layout/composition changes, explaining interactions or “hard to sketch” ideas. In time, your ability to sketch will improve along with your details in your notes. You essentially give yourself immediate feedback on your concepts, which you can then turn into case study material at the end of the design process. You can also get valuable feedback from others Just take a quick picture and send it off to your design buddies in slack, your client through email, your professor in college, etc. You can get feedback on your work and then take notes on what they respond with directly on the sketches you’ve created. We do this a lot in the Compass of Design community in order to save time staring at the same logo/website/branding package…etc. The notes will help you tremendously as you continue to go throughout the rest of the design process. Saving time fiddling with tools or getting distracted by other things. The beauty of practice You can start by drawing sticks and horrible circles. I give you full permission to suck at sketching for a while. The point is to start and never stop doing it. The more you sketch, the better your sketches become. The more you focus on making your sketches as perfect as they could be, you’re wasting the most precious thing you have in your design process. Time. Your sketch doesn’t have to be perfect. You don’t even have to draw well. I’m serious, not everyone’s sketches have to be perfect. I can’t quite get my sketches to that “viral shareability” that some of those Instagram artists/designers have. But what I can do is practice. By sketching often (even for personal stuff, not just clients), I can learn to generate more ideas quicker. This iterative approach helps me build the best details on existing ideas. I’m not spending time trying to think of the keyboard shortcuts, or using the color picker to find the best colors to start with, or finding the right actions in the dropdown menus… I’m just spending time with good music thumping in the background creating sketches with my pencil or pen. Stuck on what you need to design? “Burn“ a page in your sketchbook with some warmup doodles. Start the habit of sketching You’re going to benefit a lot by starting with your sketchbook first as long as you keep it a habit. If you don’t think you have enough time, start small. Take 5 minutes before starting your design to sketch out some quick ideas. After a while, you might be able to completely create your [insert what ever type of design you do :P] design using only a pencil and paper. Then the transition from sketch to digital is just for cleaning up your concept and presenting the end product. Just start with the 5 minutes, build the habit of sketching from there. If you ever want to get some serious design practice under your belt… Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of their craft. Every week we go over ways to market yourself better, giving and getting design feedback, improving your design professionalism, and other topics to further develop your skills. **Tap either picture **to get from where you are now to where you want to be. (: Tap on either picture to get started at compassofdesign.com Design Design Thinking UX Web Design Product Design By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out. Darian Rosebrook Brand Identity Designer for @itssomagnetic, running a design community at @compassofdesign. I write to help others grow their skills as designers. Compass of Design Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design Community to help you strengthen your skills in design, business/freelance, and marketing yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How do you say “No” to a client?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/saying-no" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do you say “No” to a client?" /><published>2017-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/saying-no</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/saying-no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/1*8I0WzJdsb343qwngwIqZvw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-you-say-no-to-a-client&quot;&gt;How do you say “No” to a client?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-might-eventually-find-yourself-in-a-position-where-you-need-to-say-no-to-a&quot;&gt;You might eventually find yourself in a position where you need to say “no” to a&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;client. Here’s how to do so professionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re designers because we’re good at making things. We use a lot of our
head-space to think of creative solutions to your client’s problems. We use art,
math, time, and resources to create something that gets our clients closer to
their goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, the world is scarce with people who value the work we do, or even
understand what we do and what it achieves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run into that from time to time when people ask me if I could just “really
quickly design a logo for their site” or like the first inquiry that I had who
thought I had agreed to do a design for him and got so angry at me he blocked me
on every social media platform…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of design won’t always be a nice and forgiving career, but the
benefits and positives outweigh the negatives for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking a lot about my design business. This has lead to a lot of
reading into the business of design, design strategy, ethics, and various topics
on building a creative business. I see it as preparation for things that I will
face when increasing the number of clients I take on, transitioning out of a day
job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things we will face a lot during our time running a design based
business is having a situation where you either have to say “no” to a client or
being in a situation where you wish you had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*ZAwQY575z1X8Jy3Q.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cost-of-saying-yes&quot;&gt;The cost of saying “Yes”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lets-start-with-what-happens-when-you-say-yes&quot;&gt;Let’s start with what happens when you say “yes.”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the words of Sean McCabe from **seanwes, **he says that the word ‘yes’ is a
very expensive word to use. When you agree to do something, you’re actively
filling time that you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Time is the most expensive resource you have. **You will continue to find that
saying no is the best tool you have to ensure your resource of time is protected
and put towards the things that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gut-check&quot;&gt;Gut check&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine saying “yes” to taking on a new client, and that client turns out to be
such a handful that you wish you hadn’t. What does your gut tell you after
agreeing to take them on as a client?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been in plenty of moments where I have regretted saying that I’ll do a
project for people. For some, the entire client wasn’t a good fit, but out of a
mindset of scarcity, I took them on anyway. Other times, it was by underbidding
the project, or not setting proper communication or expectations at the
beginning. We all learn from our past mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;so-what-do-you-need-to-do&quot;&gt;So what do you need to do?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smallbusinessforum.co/stop-saying-yes-to-everything-103876fe124?source=search_post---------0&quot;&gt;Stop saying yes to
everything.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want your “yes” to mean anything, you have to value it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; By being
selective, we are actually able to give more power and credibility to our “Yes”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;say-no-early-and-often&quot;&gt;Say “no” early and often&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;it-does-make-a-difference&quot;&gt;It does make a difference.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most recent months, I have found it easier to say no. I have a reason to
actually choose what I say because I value my free time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My free time allows me to spend more time with my Fiancé and Child.&lt;br /&gt; My free
time allows me to work on expanding the value of my design community.&lt;br /&gt; My
free time allows me to build products and courses.&lt;br /&gt; My free time allows me to
unwind and enjoy my periods of rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Say ‘no’ early and often”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;  — Blair Enns (&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2xffUgi&quot;&gt;Win without pitching
manifesto&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our problem is usually one of quality, not quantity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of quality leads we have are usually smaller than the overall leads we
get (that is if you’ve even made changes to &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmps.co/portfolio-that-converts&quot;&gt;get more leads from your
portfolio&lt;/a&gt;). We tend to compensate that
lack of quality by taking on as many other clients in as we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine, however, the ability to take on fewer clients and be paid the same, if
not more for your efforts…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selectivity is a mark of a professional. One of the defining characteristics,
building more credibility and reducing the friction of qualified leads taking
you on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-filter&quot;&gt;The filter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest mark of having a selection process is the conversations that you
have up front. When an opportunity arises, see if you can kill it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cmps.co/client-onboard-1&quot;&gt;My current filter is my design questionnaire on my
website&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve had a handful of people (&amp;lt;100)
visit my site for So Magnetic, I have received 16 inquiries since the site went
live. 9 completely filled the questionnaire out. Those were more qualified leads
than I’ve ever had before when I was just using my personal site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diving more into the projects allowed me to weed out those projects that still
were not a good fit or were better served by other freelancers (projects that
were for types of design that I don’t do). This still brings value to the client
inquiry because they then have more clarity on what they want, what they need,
and who’s best fit to help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping a client with clarity is never wasted time. You might even get good
referrals for being honest in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like our reasons for saying yes, by saying no, we are actually able to
avoid headaches later on in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-want-to-be-in-pursuit-of-that-no&quot;&gt;You want to be in pursuit of that “No”.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;need-for-no-hot-pursuit&quot;&gt;Need for “No”: Hot pursuit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for us to turn down client’s requests, we need to have set parameters
on what we actually will take on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would make sense to spend some time working on setting parameters for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The type of work you want in your portfolio&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The persona of client that you want to interact with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The level of budget projects you would like to take on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How you want to communicate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How you handle the scope of work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any part of your process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more you outline in your “ideal client” the easier it is to say “no” to
someone who doesn’t fit the bill. Positioning is a big step towards finding
those right fits. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmps.co/client-onboard-2-b&quot;&gt;Something you can do directly from your
website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Clients are going to assume responsibility for anything that you haven’t purely
defined.&lt;br /&gt; It’s your job to set expectations”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even if the opportunity is right, we still need to be selective with what we
choose to take on. By retreating just a little, someone who really does want to
continue the project will follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Speak softly and people lean toward you, speak loudly and they will back away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constantly shouting to social media that you’re available really comes across as
a hard sell. By playing “hard to get” (in terms of making the client aware
you’re selective) the client is more likely to follow you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;play-a-strong-offense&quot;&gt;Play a strong offense.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-dont-go-to-war-with-your-clients&quot;&gt;But don’t go to war with your clients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;it-is-important-to-be-firm-with-your-no&quot;&gt;It is important to be firm with your “no.”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can’t hem and haw with declining a request in a very clear and concise
manner.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we have clients that come in that would not be a good fit to work with,
(maybe because they’re a family member or anyone else you have decided is not
the ideal client), you need to say so explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-cant-just-get-rid-of-a-client&quot;&gt;You can’t just “get rid” of a client.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;so-please-for-the-love-of-all-that-is-of-an-elevated-sort-of-manner&quot;&gt;So please, for the love of all that is of an elevated sort of manner…&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-not&quot;&gt;do not:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quote an abnormally high rate:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a dishonest and arbitrary way of trying to get rid of someone. If you
don’t want to work with them, say no. Charging them higher than the rest of your
clients based on the fact that you don’t want to work with them just means
you’ll have to take on the client if they accept to not be rude and be stuck
with a client you didn’t want to work with in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell them you’re too busy when you’re really not. E.g. “I can’t at this
time”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Again, this means that should you then post on social media that you’re taking
on new clients, your client inquiry will see right through your BS and put in
their request again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In either case above, if they are someone you’d like to work with, consider a
retainer fee for their spot on your calendar so that you can work together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask them to go through your questionnaire when you already know it’s not a
good fit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unless you really do like wasting people’s time for the fun of it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give any reason outside the truth (probably distilled)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t tell them upfront that their project sucks. Don’t tell them that they’re
an asshat. But let them know in a professional manner that they don’t fit the
profile of clients that you work with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are lies, and they will require maintenance to keep up. Avoid the nonsense
by being straightforward up-front, and honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;do-not-compromise&quot;&gt;Do not compromise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never compromise your professionalism. Never compromise on your ethics. Never
compromise on morals. Never compromise on price. Never do work for free in
exchange for “Exposure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere along the lines, if you’re running into areas where you are having to
consider compromising in these areas, there’s a hole in the process. The beauty
of that is because &lt;strong&gt;you as a professional have the responsibility and
capability to change things&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though you might be in the situation right now, you can take time after the
engagement to audit your process and see why the situation popped up and do
something to safeguard against it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;so-what-do-you-say&quot;&gt;So what do you say?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You be honest. Tell them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey, [name]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks so much for getting in touch. I really appreciate you taking the time to
send an inquiry and provide your project information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very selective about the projects I take on. After much consideration with
your project request, based on my project criteria, I will have to decline your
project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do want to sincerely thank you for your time and interest.&lt;br /&gt; If you would
like, I do have colleages I can pass your request along to, just let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[your name]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;surprise&quot;&gt;Surprise!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You still have me over here, waiting for you to revise this design for the 8th
time”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-client-you-already-have&quot;&gt;The client you already have&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that all of these situations above tend to safeguard us from taking on
difficult clients that aren’t a good fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what happens when you already have a client that is requesting things
that you know will be (even just slightly) outside of what you both agreed on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But it’s a small change, it shouldn’t take you any time at all”&lt;br /&gt; “I’m the
one paying for this project”&lt;br /&gt; “We need to change [date, request, colors,
etc]”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;have-a-conversation-first&quot;&gt;Have a conversation first&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about being in the client engagement already makes this a very sticky,
tricky, and potentially legal battle to fight with clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to have empathy for where the client is coming from and you need to
have conversations around what the client’s expectations are. Maybe the request
is a simple misunderstanding, and maybe the request is due to the client needing
to take charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your responsibility to clear this up and continue the project the best you
can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-firm&quot;&gt;Be firm&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won’t be easy to navigate having to tell a current client “no” during an
active client engagement. For whatever reason, your client has come to you in
order to add a detail, start another revision, change the style completely, or
go back and change a small thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You need to have certain processes in place in order to safeguard yourself
from situations like this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything up to this point has been as part of your written or un-written
design process, contract, or design proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere along the way, there was a miscommunication, either you weren’t able
to fully understand the client’s vision (or they couldn’t convey it clear
enough), or the client misunderstands what you both agreed upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-first-line-of-action-is-to-check-the-request&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first line of action is to check the request.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does this request require me to compromise (see the last section) my
professionalism?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much time and effort will this request take to complete?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this going to make or break our client engagement?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to **check the list above to see if this request is going to be
feasible **within the client’s scope of project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You then need to **audit the request to see if there was any miscommunication
**between you two that got you to where you are now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have to &lt;strong&gt;tell your client that you cannot do the request **because of
processes in place, time restraints, feasibility, ethics. etc. Just **do not
lie. Be honest.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If saying “no” to the request makes the client want to break the engagement, you
may have to consider 2 things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go along with the request (as long as it doesn’t break too much) and fix your
process to avoid that in the future. Take this as a clear example of what to
avoid/fix for future engagements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a sit down with the client, redo the project discovery to get a full and
complete picture of where the client was expecting the project to go, if any
goals have changed, clearing up any misconceptions and then starting the process
from there with a new proposal and contract.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it will break the engagement, and it will compromise your integrity as a
person, professional, or a designer. Don’t let it devalue the work we do as
designers. Tell the client no. Firmly. And that the course of action is to
continue with the project as planned, or to stop the project entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;seek-outside-help&quot;&gt;Seek outside help&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having someone outside of the situation to go to can be of great help when
looking for advice. Whether it be a mentor, someone you can go to for legal
advice, colleagues, other designers, you might be able to get help with
navigating the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These situations aren’t easy to navigate at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want help, &lt;a href=&quot;https://compassofdesign.com/community&quot;&gt;we have a community of
designers&lt;/a&gt; from UX, UI, Web, Graphic,
Data, Print designers, along with developers of sorts who have all had
experience with the aspects of client work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-end&quot;&gt;In the end&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking time to put processes in place in order to avoid these situations will be
your best armor for avoiding these situations entirely. But eventually, there’s
going to be a situation where you have to say “no.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say so with a firm, clear, and consise manner that is professional. Don’t burn
bridges. Remember that word of mouth is still your biggest ally in client work,
and your professionalism on how you handle these situations will determine
whether that word of mouth helps you or hinders you when searching for new
clients to work with.&lt;br /&gt;  &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Don’t be afraid to tell a client no in order
to protect the value of your work and the work of every other designer out there
in the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*mo7_gcoDhIhJHCOLPxMfLg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-you-ever-want-to-learn-more-about-design-for-clients&quot;&gt;If you ever want to learn more about design for clients…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of
their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week we go over ways to market yourself better, giving and getting design
feedback, improving your design professionalism, and other topics to further
develop your skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tap either picture to get from where you are now to where you want to be. (:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;Tap on either picture to get started at compassofdesign.com&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/freelancing?source=post&quot;&gt;Freelancing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/design?source=post&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/entrepreneurship?source=post&quot;&gt;Entrepreneurship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/consulting?source=post&quot;&gt;Consulting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/web-development?source=post&quot;&gt;Web
Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;darian-rosebrook&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/@darianrosebrook&quot;&gt;Darian Rosebrook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brand Identity Designer for  &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/itssomagnetic&quot;&gt;@itssomagnetic&lt;/a&gt;,
running a design community at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/compassofdesign&quot;&gt;@compassofdesign&lt;/a&gt;. I write to help others
grow their skills as designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;compass-of-design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/?source=footer_card&quot;&gt;Compass of Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design
Community to help you strengthen your design skills, business/freelance ethics,
and design professionalism. Join us in the community or get on the newsletter to
get access to exclusive content.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="article" /><summary type="html">How do you say “No” to a client? You might eventually find yourself in a position where you need to say “no” to a client. Here’s how to do so professionally. We’re designers because we’re good at making things. We use a lot of our head-space to think of creative solutions to your client’s problems. We use art, math, time, and resources to create something that gets our clients closer to their goals. The thing is, the world is scarce with people who value the work we do, or even understand what we do and what it achieves. I run into that from time to time when people ask me if I could just “really quickly design a logo for their site” or like the first inquiry that I had who thought I had agreed to do a design for him and got so angry at me he blocked me on every social media platform… The world of design won’t always be a nice and forgiving career, but the benefits and positives outweigh the negatives for sure. I have been thinking a lot about my design business. This has lead to a lot of reading into the business of design, design strategy, ethics, and various topics on building a creative business. I see it as preparation for things that I will face when increasing the number of clients I take on, transitioning out of a day job. One of the things we will face a lot during our time running a design based business is having a situation where you either have to say “no” to a client or being in a situation where you wish you had. The cost of saying “Yes” Let’s start with what happens when you say “yes.” In the words of Sean McCabe from **seanwes, **he says that the word ‘yes’ is a very expensive word to use. When you agree to do something, you’re actively filling time that you have. **Time is the most expensive resource you have. **You will continue to find that saying no is the best tool you have to ensure your resource of time is protected and put towards the things that matter. Gut check Imagine saying “yes” to taking on a new client, and that client turns out to be such a handful that you wish you hadn’t. What does your gut tell you after agreeing to take them on as a client? I have been in plenty of moments where I have regretted saying that I’ll do a project for people. For some, the entire client wasn’t a good fit, but out of a mindset of scarcity, I took them on anyway. Other times, it was by underbidding the project, or not setting proper communication or expectations at the beginning. We all learn from our past mistakes. So what do you need to do? Stop saying yes to everything. If you want your “yes” to mean anything, you have to value it. By being selective, we are actually able to give more power and credibility to our “Yes” Say “no” early and often It does make a difference. In the most recent months, I have found it easier to say no. I have a reason to actually choose what I say because I value my free time. My free time allows me to spend more time with my Fiancé and Child. My free time allows me to work on expanding the value of my design community. My free time allows me to build products and courses. My free time allows me to unwind and enjoy my periods of rest. “Say ‘no’ early and often” — Blair Enns (Win without pitching manifesto) Our problem is usually one of quality, not quantity. A number of quality leads we have are usually smaller than the overall leads we get (that is if you’ve even made changes to get more leads from your portfolio). We tend to compensate that lack of quality by taking on as many other clients in as we can. Imagine, however, the ability to take on fewer clients and be paid the same, if not more for your efforts… Selectivity is a mark of a professional. One of the defining characteristics, building more credibility and reducing the friction of qualified leads taking you on. The filter The easiest mark of having a selection process is the conversations that you have up front. When an opportunity arises, see if you can kill it. My current filter is my design questionnaire on my website. I’ve had a handful of people (&amp;lt;100) visit my site for So Magnetic, I have received 16 inquiries since the site went live. 9 completely filled the questionnaire out. Those were more qualified leads than I’ve ever had before when I was just using my personal site. Diving more into the projects allowed me to weed out those projects that still were not a good fit or were better served by other freelancers (projects that were for types of design that I don’t do). This still brings value to the client inquiry because they then have more clarity on what they want, what they need, and who’s best fit to help them. Helping a client with clarity is never wasted time. You might even get good referrals for being honest in the first place. Just like our reasons for saying yes, by saying no, we are actually able to avoid headaches later on in the process. You want to be in pursuit of that “No”. Need for “No”: Hot pursuit In order for us to turn down client’s requests, we need to have set parameters on what we actually will take on. It would make sense to spend some time working on setting parameters for: The type of work you want in your portfolio The persona of client that you want to interact with The level of budget projects you would like to take on How you want to communicate How you handle the scope of work Any part of your process etc The more you outline in your “ideal client” the easier it is to say “no” to someone who doesn’t fit the bill. Positioning is a big step towards finding those right fits. Something you can do directly from your website. “Clients are going to assume responsibility for anything that you haven’t purely defined. It’s your job to set expectations” So even if the opportunity is right, we still need to be selective with what we choose to take on. By retreating just a little, someone who really does want to continue the project will follow. “Speak softly and people lean toward you, speak loudly and they will back away.” Constantly shouting to social media that you’re available really comes across as a hard sell. By playing “hard to get” (in terms of making the client aware you’re selective) the client is more likely to follow you. Play a strong offense. But don’t go to war with your clients It is important to be firm with your “no.” You can’t hem and haw with declining a request in a very clear and concise manner. When we have clients that come in that would not be a good fit to work with, (maybe because they’re a family member or anyone else you have decided is not the ideal client), you need to say so explicitly. You can’t just “get rid” of a client. So please, for the love of all that is of an elevated sort of manner… do not: Quote an abnormally high rate: This is a dishonest and arbitrary way of trying to get rid of someone. If you don’t want to work with them, say no. Charging them higher than the rest of your clients based on the fact that you don’t want to work with them just means you’ll have to take on the client if they accept to not be rude and be stuck with a client you didn’t want to work with in the first place. Tell them you’re too busy when you’re really not. E.g. “I can’t at this time” Again, this means that should you then post on social media that you’re taking on new clients, your client inquiry will see right through your BS and put in their request again. In either case above, if they are someone you’d like to work with, consider a retainer fee for their spot on your calendar so that you can work together. Ask them to go through your questionnaire when you already know it’s not a good fit Unless you really do like wasting people’s time for the fun of it. Give any reason outside the truth (probably distilled) Don’t tell them upfront that their project sucks. Don’t tell them that they’re an asshat. But let them know in a professional manner that they don’t fit the profile of clients that you work with. These are lies, and they will require maintenance to keep up. Avoid the nonsense by being straightforward up-front, and honest. Do not compromise Never compromise your professionalism. Never compromise on your ethics. Never compromise on morals. Never compromise on price. Never do work for free in exchange for “Exposure.” Somewhere along the lines, if you’re running into areas where you are having to consider compromising in these areas, there’s a hole in the process. The beauty of that is because you as a professional have the responsibility and capability to change things. Though you might be in the situation right now, you can take time after the engagement to audit your process and see why the situation popped up and do something to safeguard against it in the future. So what do you say? You be honest. Tell them: Hey, [name] Thanks so much for getting in touch. I really appreciate you taking the time to send an inquiry and provide your project information. I am very selective about the projects I take on. After much consideration with your project request, based on my project criteria, I will have to decline your project. I do want to sincerely thank you for your time and interest. If you would like, I do have colleages I can pass your request along to, just let me know. All the best, [your name] Surprise! “You still have me over here, waiting for you to revise this design for the 8th time” The client you already have I know that all of these situations above tend to safeguard us from taking on difficult clients that aren’t a good fit. However, what happens when you already have a client that is requesting things that you know will be (even just slightly) outside of what you both agreed on? “But it’s a small change, it shouldn’t take you any time at all” “I’m the one paying for this project” “We need to change [date, request, colors, etc]” Have a conversation first The thing about being in the client engagement already makes this a very sticky, tricky, and potentially legal battle to fight with clients. You need to have empathy for where the client is coming from and you need to have conversations around what the client’s expectations are. Maybe the request is a simple misunderstanding, and maybe the request is due to the client needing to take charge. It’s your responsibility to clear this up and continue the project the best you can. Be firm It won’t be easy to navigate having to tell a current client “no” during an active client engagement. For whatever reason, your client has come to you in order to add a detail, start another revision, change the style completely, or go back and change a small thing. You need to have certain processes in place in order to safeguard yourself from situations like this. Everything up to this point has been as part of your written or un-written design process, contract, or design proposal. Somewhere along the way, there was a miscommunication, either you weren’t able to fully understand the client’s vision (or they couldn’t convey it clear enough), or the client misunderstands what you both agreed upon. The first line of action is to check the request. Does this request require me to compromise (see the last section) my professionalism? How much time and effort will this request take to complete? Is this going to make or break our client engagement? You need to **check the list above to see if this request is going to be feasible **within the client’s scope of project. You then need to **audit the request to see if there was any miscommunication **between you two that got you to where you are now. You may have to tell your client that you cannot do the request **because of processes in place, time restraints, feasibility, ethics. etc. Just **do not lie. Be honest. If saying “no” to the request makes the client want to break the engagement, you may have to consider 2 things: Go along with the request (as long as it doesn’t break too much) and fix your process to avoid that in the future. Take this as a clear example of what to avoid/fix for future engagements. Have a sit down with the client, redo the project discovery to get a full and complete picture of where the client was expecting the project to go, if any goals have changed, clearing up any misconceptions and then starting the process from there with a new proposal and contract. If it will break the engagement, and it will compromise your integrity as a person, professional, or a designer. Don’t let it devalue the work we do as designers. Tell the client no. Firmly. And that the course of action is to continue with the project as planned, or to stop the project entirely. Seek outside help Having someone outside of the situation to go to can be of great help when looking for advice. Whether it be a mentor, someone you can go to for legal advice, colleagues, other designers, you might be able to get help with navigating the situation. These situations aren’t easy to navigate at all. If you want help, we have a community of designers from UX, UI, Web, Graphic, Data, Print designers, along with developers of sorts who have all had experience with the aspects of client work. In the end Taking time to put processes in place in order to avoid these situations will be your best armor for avoiding these situations entirely. But eventually, there’s going to be a situation where you have to say “no.” Say so with a firm, clear, and consise manner that is professional. Don’t burn bridges. Remember that word of mouth is still your biggest ally in client work, and your professionalism on how you handle these situations will determine whether that word of mouth helps you or hinders you when searching for new clients to work with. Don’t be afraid to tell a client no in order to protect the value of your work and the work of every other designer out there in the world. If you ever want to learn more about design for clients… Come join other like-minded designers who are working at becoming masters of their craft. Every week we go over ways to market yourself better, giving and getting design feedback, improving your design professionalism, and other topics to further develop your skills. Tap either picture to get from where you are now to where you want to be. (: Tap on either picture to get started at compassofdesign.com Freelancing Design Entrepreneurship Consulting Web Development By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out. Darian Rosebrook Brand Identity Designer for @itssomagnetic, running a design community at @compassofdesign. I write to help others grow their skills as designers. Compass of Design Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design Community to help you strengthen your design skills, business/freelance ethics, and design professionalism. Join us in the community or get on the newsletter to get access to exclusive content.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Design bound by ethics — Being able to sleep at night after work.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/design-ethics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design bound by ethics — Being able to sleep at night after work." /><published>2017-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/design-ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/design-ethics">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/1*gwmB5no8gS-D6y4Rq91X3Q.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;design-bound-by-ethics&quot;&gt;Design bound by ethics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;being-able-to-sleep-at-night-after-work&quot;&gt;Being able to sleep at night after work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is a beautiful thing. You have the ability to take an idea effectively
make it a great experience for another person. In other words, &lt;strong&gt;your design has
the power to affect the people that come face to face with it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have that type of role in the design process of these ideas, you are
bound ethically to how your design helps or hinders someone their goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Great design blends in and furthers the goals of the person it’s used by.Bad
design is, in it’s purest form, harmful to the person it’s consumed by.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether their goals are: physical, emotional, psychological, financial… there is
something that person needs to accomplish with something that you have designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If they can’t accomplish their goals, or are even hindered by it trying to use
it, then you are essentially at fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-great-thing-is-that-if-its-partly-your-fault-you-are-aware-and-now-have&quot;&gt;The great thing is that if it’s partly your fault, you are aware and now have&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the ability to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*uVp-iKcCkSL2DPtDM5NKYQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-responsibility&quot;&gt;Your responsibility:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-accountable-to-the-intended-audience&quot;&gt;Be accountable to the intended audience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us are at the forefront of the user-experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drive people to choose options, to favor on choice over the other. We display
information in ways we believe that someone should consume the content. We
design the way a product is intended to be used. We are then responsible in part
for making sure that we did our best to help them accomplish what they need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t always predict how something you made will be used though, because at
most, we design for human beings. Therefore, we can not scapegoat the fact that
you did design that ‘thing.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to quote a paragraph from Mike Montiero &lt;a href=&quot;https://deardesignstudent.com/ethics-and-paying-rent-86e972ce9015&quot;&gt;about this
topic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Design is a discipline of action. You are responsible for what you put into the
world. It has your name on it. And while it is certainly impossible to predict
how any of your work may be used, it shouldn’t be a surprise when work that is
meant to hurt someone fulfills its mission. We cannot be surprised when a gun we
designed kills someone. We cannot be surprised when a database we designed to
catalog immigrants gets those immigrants deported. When we knowingly produce
work that is intended to harm, we are abdicating our responsibility. When we
ignorantly produce work that harms others because we didn’t consider the full
ramifications of that work, we are doubly guilty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The work you bring into the world is your legacy. It will outlive you. And it
will speak for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You cannot claim ignorance if the thing was intended to harm. However, you want
to make sure you do your due-diligence when designing something, and ask
yourself some hard questions about the intent behind the design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is this being designed to help people or is this to help the company at the
people’s expense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dark-ux&quot;&gt;Dark UX:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-wary-of-misleading-or-misdirecting&quot;&gt;Be wary of misleading or misdirecting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark UX, or the dark patterns of user experience, are created when the goals of
the company aren’t aligned with the goals of the end user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are times where the company believes its goals are more important than the
end user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a designer, &lt;strong&gt;your work serves the goals of the people who are face-to-face
with your design&lt;/strong&gt;. You need to understand that &lt;strong&gt;your employer or your client
might not see it that way&lt;/strong&gt;. So based on the goals of the company you might find
yourself getting close to compromising your ethical/moral boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your moral boundaries are being tested, you must decide to put yourself in
their shoes. If you came across this design, would you actually understand or
want what is being displayed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark UX shows up in many places now around the internet in ways you might not
expect. This trend is not okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you tried to finish reading a page on the internet, went to exit the page,
and then were greeted by a really obstructing pop-up box? Do you remember what
it said?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of message that is popping up in pop-up form is what’s called
“&lt;a href=&quot;http://confirmshaming.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;confirm shaming&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confirm shaming happens when you see a pop up that offers something to the end
user with exchange for an email address or purchase. However, should you
&lt;strong&gt;choose to opt-out of the option you have to click a self-deprecating
response&lt;/strong&gt; much like these below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;The images above do what I just talked about. They make the popup super
“in-your-face” and really try to hide the option they don’t want you to choose.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dark patterns are dangerous in design because they trick the user into doing
something that they don’t want to do or benefit them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of dark ux patterns to look into. I’ll highlight some of the
more prominent ones I’ve seen, but you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://darkpatterns.org/types-of-dark-pattern&quot;&gt;check this list here to educate
yourself on ones to avoid doing
&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**(This) **&lt;a href=&quot;http://confirmshaming.tumblr.com/page/3&quot;&gt;Confirm Shaming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Guilt-tripping you into taking their action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Bait and Switch **&lt;br /&gt; Your end-user sets out to do one thing, but a
different, undesirable thing happens instead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disguised Ads&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Some of these look like legitimate links or articles, but
in fact are pure advertisements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forced Continuity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; When your free trial with a service comes to an end
and your credit card silently starts getting charged without any warning. In
some cases this is made even worse by making it difficult to cancel the
membership.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Privacy Zuckering **&lt;br /&gt; You are tricked into publicly sharing more
information about yourself than you really intended to. Named after Facebook CEO
Mark Zuckerberg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;**Roach Motel **&lt;br /&gt; The design makes it very easy for you to get into a certain
situation, but then makes it hard for you to get out of it (e.g. a
subscription).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The opt-out/opt-in distraction.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Not giving a clear choice on what you’re
signing up for or not signing up for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These &lt;strong&gt;dark patterns are completely avoidable when you learn what they are&lt;/strong&gt;.
It is our duty to notice these when we are asked to include them in our designs,
speaking out against them with our moral fiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;presenting-data&quot;&gt;Presenting Data:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;avoiding-the-pitfalls-of-misrepresentation&quot;&gt;Avoiding the pitfalls of misrepresentation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;This still is from&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/bY8-TUD3_Zo?t=7&quot;&gt; a Film Theory video on
YouTube&lt;/a&gt; from the first 60 seconds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research in this area is sparse, but I wanted to talk about the way we
present data. The image/link above here sparked my interest. It’s from a
theorist who pulls apart video games and film/tv and ultimately pulls theories
together that drive the story, the cultural reference, or the
science/feasibility of certain aspects of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 60 seconds of the video is what I’m referencing.** The representation
of data.**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can choose to watch the rest of the video, but only the first minute shows
what I’m talking about. If you don’t watch it, he basically says that “Data”
doesn’t lie, but the way that “data” is represented does. We rely on accurate
data in order to make decisions, to save lives, to inform the public, etc. When
we can’t parse the information correctly, we lose our clarity on what to do with
the information. In the example, they present a presidential candidate’s rating
in the last position even though his data is higher than the one before him,
indicating that he’s in last for the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.statisticshowto.com/misleading-graphs/&quot;&gt; been numerous accounts of this in the
past,&lt;/a&gt; and it’s an issue that
we’ll continue to deal with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datapine.com/blog/misleading-data-visualization-examples/&quot;&gt;intentional
&lt;/a&gt;or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2017/01/3-ways-data-dashboards-can-mislead-you&quot;&gt;un-intentional&lt;/a&gt;,
the way we visualize data needs to be accurate without bias or implying things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it just needs to be designed well. We need to remember this when we
represent this data to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nevona/status/869780302813646849&quot;&gt;Here, have a pie chart that was poorly
designed.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption_hack&quot;&gt;or this one too&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-balance-of-power&quot;&gt;The Balance of Power:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;your-work-has-the-power-of-change&quot;&gt;Your work has the power of change&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design and art have always had a spot in history. Most of the best examples of
this has been during influential and radical change of that period’s society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether that change has been for the better (acceptance, peace, unity,
education, cultural advancement) or for worse (war, fear mongering, control,
defamation, death and destruction), &lt;strong&gt;the power of design is it’s power to
change.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the ability to craft the way people view current issues through art; the
power to influence minds through design, to strike a chord with masses of people
with vision, to guide change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A lot of us are not flexing our ability to make this change happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our world today, we focus so hard on being politically correct; even in
countries where there are direct consequences for our actions. This causes us to
not tread on topics and ideas that people need to know about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revolutions are built on the essence of human creativity, because art itself is
the human spirit being free and exercising choice. The same can be said about
instating change and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;we-have-the-power-we-have-the-control&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We have the power, we have the control.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-we-choose-to-do-with-that-is-our-own-issue&quot;&gt;What we choose to do with that is our own issue.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;id-rather-see-that-used-for-good&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’d rather see that used for good.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avoiding-harming-others&quot;&gt;Avoiding harming others&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;accessibility-incluson-fairness-and-harm&quot;&gt;Accessibility, incluson, fairness and harm&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the United States, the percentage of organ donors through the nation
varies state to state. Even as a whole, 45% of the U.S. is a declared organ
donor (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/11/why-dont-people-want-to-donate-their-organs/382297/&quot;&gt;based off 2012
data&lt;/a&gt;,
Donate Life states for 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.donatelife.net/mission-vision/&quot;&gt;it’s closer to
56%&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in other areas of the world, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.behaviouraldesign.com/2015/08/11/why-99-of-austrians-donate-their-organs/#sthash.PSy0gR7c.dpbs&quot;&gt;there’s a large amount of countries with
higher than
80%&lt;/a&gt;
rates of organ donors. A lot of it &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesocietypages.org/socimages/2015/09/11/decision-making-and-the-options-were-offered/&quot;&gt;comes down to the way they display the
default
choice.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The countries that have the higher ratings use becoming an organ donor as the
default choice (you’d have to opt-out of being a donor) where the other
countries (and roughing this data here) use an opt-in choice to become a donor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I view organ donation a good thing (not looking to spark politics, just
stating) there are other examples for the &lt;strong&gt;default design that can ultimately
harm the people intended to use these designs&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of a recent experience trying to switch phone carriers that cost us
nearly $1,500.00 to fix. We were automatically added a phone line by our old
carrier we didn’t need because we were “given” (never actually received it) by
default a new wifi-hotspot for signing up for a certain plan. We didn’t know
about it because of automatic billing and payments so when we went to switch to
the new plan, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/d_evyn/status/912127961951637504&quot;&gt;the old account never
closed.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default choice here was not being told we can opt out, nor telling us we
were being added to the additional plan in the contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data within was hidden underneath massive amounts of text during something
that usually takes a while to sign up for. Ultimately it was our fault for not
reading through word by word, but the way the process was designed ultimately
cost us a lot of money to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disability in the United States is something that we are well aware of. With 19%
of the U.S. living with a form of disability in 2010 (solid data seems to take a
while to be presented because all numbers I’ve found for 2016 or 2017 widely
vary), that means nearly 56 million Americans (or 1 out of 5) would have
difficulty using something designed for someone without the disability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of inclusion is in fact harmful to the experience of these people, even
if it was an oversight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things my brother, who is left handed, has brought to my attention is
that left-handed people have and continue to die from operating equipment that
was designed for right-handed people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I’ve had a hard time verifying this with numbers, I have found (even from
practicing being left-handed) that &lt;a href=&quot;https://fishofgold.net/2013/06/06/the-worst-products-for-left-handed-people/&quot;&gt;there are tons of products that are poorly
designed for left-handed
people.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as designers must consider every outlier of use cases that ultimately
includes every able and inable bodied persons out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessability is still an issue when we consider every state, every user, every
capability… We can run our budgets to the ground with trying to cover all bases.
But if you neglect inclusivity, you are essentially designing a wall to block
someone from your creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true with everything from gender bias, racial acceptance, cultural
differences, financial classes, there always seems to be something that drives
other humans to be “separate” from another group. People will even &lt;a href=&quot;https://explorable.com/research-bias&quot;&gt;research
something in bias just to prove a point&lt;/a&gt;,
only representing things that make that report look good. Others blatantly
exclude others because of minor differences in choice, appearance, orientation,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to empowering disgusting excuses for human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing trumps the good intentions of people more than biased hatred in the
world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who was raised kind of sheltered to the world, in a good home, with
morals, I’m constantly shocked by the actions of others. Though I am not perfect
myself, I try to see things from the views of others, and am shocked by how
prevalent the disparity between two seemingly different groups of people echo
through our design world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of the fact that gender roles have been a “conventional ‘Male’ and
‘Female’ choice” as an old “ism” that we have kept. We could just alphabetize
the option or kill it entirely from our forms. I recognize the needs for medical
use as another issue, but for most daily use in design, that data is
unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to avoid designing our work to favor any particular group and their
ability, enabling them to perceive themselves as “ahead of” or “above another”
human being. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/about/corporate-responsibility/accessibility&quot;&gt;data exists to be able to design our things to include
others&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disparity doesn’t stop, unless we help stop it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re all made of the same stuff, born the same way, and we will all die the
same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about ethics is that we think that it’s too much to deal with, or that
there’s no way to change the way the world works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can defeat disparity through our careers as designers. We need to focus on
being a more effective designer, working on mastering the founding principles
and holding you and the community accountable for what you all design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we will have the power to change the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to improve my own skills and pass along that knowledge to
others. Remember keep your ethics in check and help educate those you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take charge, and make change happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/design?source=post&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/ethics?source=post&quot;&gt;Ethics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/design-thinking?source=post&quot;&gt;Design
Thinking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/ux?source=post&quot;&gt;UX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/tagged/marketing?source=post&quot;&gt;Marketing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;darian-rosebrook&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/@darianrosebrook&quot;&gt;Darian Rosebrook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brand Identity Designer for &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/itssomagnetic&quot;&gt;@itssomagnetic&lt;/a&gt;,
running a design community at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/compassofdesign&quot;&gt;@compassofdesign&lt;/a&gt;. I write to help others
grow their skills as designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;compass-of-design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://read.compassofdesign.com/?source=footer_card&quot;&gt;Compass of Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design
Community to help you strengthen your design skills, business/freelance ethics,
and design professionalism. Join us in the community or get on the newsletter to
get access to exclusive content.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Design bound by ethics Being able to sleep at night after work Design is a beautiful thing. You have the ability to take an idea effectively make it a great experience for another person. In other words, your design has the power to affect the people that come face to face with it. When you have that type of role in the design process of these ideas, you are bound ethically to how your design helps or hinders someone their goal. Great design blends in and furthers the goals of the person it’s used by.Bad design is, in it’s purest form, harmful to the person it’s consumed by. Whether their goals are: physical, emotional, psychological, financial… there is something that person needs to accomplish with something that you have designed. If they can’t accomplish their goals, or are even hindered by it trying to use it, then you are essentially at fault. The great thing is that if it’s partly your fault, you are aware and now have the ability to fix it. Your responsibility: Be accountable to the intended audience Most of us are at the forefront of the user-experience. We drive people to choose options, to favor on choice over the other. We display information in ways we believe that someone should consume the content. We design the way a product is intended to be used. We are then responsible in part for making sure that we did our best to help them accomplish what they need to. You can’t always predict how something you made will be used though, because at most, we design for human beings. Therefore, we can not scapegoat the fact that you did design that ‘thing.’ I want to quote a paragraph from Mike Montiero about this topic. Design is a discipline of action. You are responsible for what you put into the world. It has your name on it. And while it is certainly impossible to predict how any of your work may be used, it shouldn’t be a surprise when work that is meant to hurt someone fulfills its mission. We cannot be surprised when a gun we designed kills someone. We cannot be surprised when a database we designed to catalog immigrants gets those immigrants deported. When we knowingly produce work that is intended to harm, we are abdicating our responsibility. When we ignorantly produce work that harms others because we didn’t consider the full ramifications of that work, we are doubly guilty. The work you bring into the world is your legacy. It will outlive you. And it will speak for you. You cannot claim ignorance if the thing was intended to harm. However, you want to make sure you do your due-diligence when designing something, and ask yourself some hard questions about the intent behind the design. Is this being designed to help people or is this to help the company at the people’s expense? Dark UX: Be wary of misleading or misdirecting Dark UX, or the dark patterns of user experience, are created when the goals of the company aren’t aligned with the goals of the end user. There are times where the company believes its goals are more important than the end user. As a designer, your work serves the goals of the people who are face-to-face with your design. You need to understand that your employer or your client might not see it that way. So based on the goals of the company you might find yourself getting close to compromising your ethical/moral boundaries. When your moral boundaries are being tested, you must decide to put yourself in their shoes. If you came across this design, would you actually understand or want what is being displayed? Dark UX shows up in many places now around the internet in ways you might not expect. This trend is not okay. Have you tried to finish reading a page on the internet, went to exit the page, and then were greeted by a really obstructing pop-up box? Do you remember what it said? This kind of message that is popping up in pop-up form is what’s called “confirm shaming.” Confirm shaming happens when you see a pop up that offers something to the end user with exchange for an email address or purchase. However, should you choose to opt-out of the option you have to click a self-deprecating response much like these below. The images above do what I just talked about. They make the popup super “in-your-face” and really try to hide the option they don’t want you to choose. Dark patterns are dangerous in design because they trick the user into doing something that they don’t want to do or benefit them. There are a ton of dark ux patterns to look into. I’ll highlight some of the more prominent ones I’ve seen, but you can check this list here to educate yourself on ones to avoid doing : **(This) **Confirm Shaming Guilt-tripping you into taking their action. **Bait and Switch ** Your end-user sets out to do one thing, but a different, undesirable thing happens instead. Disguised Ads Some of these look like legitimate links or articles, but in fact are pure advertisements. Forced Continuity When your free trial with a service comes to an end and your credit card silently starts getting charged without any warning. In some cases this is made even worse by making it difficult to cancel the membership. **Privacy Zuckering ** You are tricked into publicly sharing more information about yourself than you really intended to. Named after Facebook CEO Mark Zuckerberg. **Roach Motel ** The design makes it very easy for you to get into a certain situation, but then makes it hard for you to get out of it (e.g. a subscription). The opt-out/opt-in distraction. Not giving a clear choice on what you’re signing up for or not signing up for. These dark patterns are completely avoidable when you learn what they are. It is our duty to notice these when we are asked to include them in our designs, speaking out against them with our moral fiber. Presenting Data: Avoiding the pitfalls of misrepresentation This still is from a Film Theory video on YouTube from the first 60 seconds My research in this area is sparse, but I wanted to talk about the way we present data. The image/link above here sparked my interest. It’s from a theorist who pulls apart video games and film/tv and ultimately pulls theories together that drive the story, the cultural reference, or the science/feasibility of certain aspects of them. The first 60 seconds of the video is what I’m referencing.** The representation of data.** You can choose to watch the rest of the video, but only the first minute shows what I’m talking about. If you don’t watch it, he basically says that “Data” doesn’t lie, but the way that “data” is represented does. We rely on accurate data in order to make decisions, to save lives, to inform the public, etc. When we can’t parse the information correctly, we lose our clarity on what to do with the information. In the example, they present a presidential candidate’s rating in the last position even though his data is higher than the one before him, indicating that he’s in last for the race. There have been numerous accounts of this in the past, and it’s an issue that we’ll continue to deal with Whether intentional or un-intentional, the way we visualize data needs to be accurate without bias or implying things. Also, it just needs to be designed well. We need to remember this when we represent this data to the public. Here, have a pie chart that was poorly designed. or this one too The Balance of Power: Your work has the power of change Design and art have always had a spot in history. Most of the best examples of this has been during influential and radical change of that period’s society. Whether that change has been for the better (acceptance, peace, unity, education, cultural advancement) or for worse (war, fear mongering, control, defamation, death and destruction), the power of design is it’s power to change. We have the ability to craft the way people view current issues through art; the power to influence minds through design, to strike a chord with masses of people with vision, to guide change. A lot of us are not flexing our ability to make this change happen. In our world today, we focus so hard on being politically correct; even in countries where there are direct consequences for our actions. This causes us to not tread on topics and ideas that people need to know about. Revolutions are built on the essence of human creativity, because art itself is the human spirit being free and exercising choice. The same can be said about instating change and control. We have the power, we have the control. What we choose to do with that is our own issue. I’d rather see that used for good. Avoiding harming others Accessibility, incluson, fairness and harm Here in the United States, the percentage of organ donors through the nation varies state to state. Even as a whole, 45% of the U.S. is a declared organ donor (based off 2012 data, Donate Life states for 2017, it’s closer to 56%) However, in other areas of the world, there’s a large amount of countries with higher than 80% rates of organ donors. A lot of it comes down to the way they display the default choice. The countries that have the higher ratings use becoming an organ donor as the default choice (you’d have to opt-out of being a donor) where the other countries (and roughing this data here) use an opt-in choice to become a donor. Though I view organ donation a good thing (not looking to spark politics, just stating) there are other examples for the default design that can ultimately harm the people intended to use these designs. Thinking of a recent experience trying to switch phone carriers that cost us nearly $1,500.00 to fix. We were automatically added a phone line by our old carrier we didn’t need because we were “given” (never actually received it) by default a new wifi-hotspot for signing up for a certain plan. We didn’t know about it because of automatic billing and payments so when we went to switch to the new plan, the old account never closed. The default choice here was not being told we can opt out, nor telling us we were being added to the additional plan in the contract. The data within was hidden underneath massive amounts of text during something that usually takes a while to sign up for. Ultimately it was our fault for not reading through word by word, but the way the process was designed ultimately cost us a lot of money to fix. Accessibility Disability in the United States is something that we are well aware of. With 19% of the U.S. living with a form of disability in 2010 (solid data seems to take a while to be presented because all numbers I’ve found for 2016 or 2017 widely vary), that means nearly 56 million Americans (or 1 out of 5) would have difficulty using something designed for someone without the disability. The lack of inclusion is in fact harmful to the experience of these people, even if it was an oversight. One of the things my brother, who is left handed, has brought to my attention is that left-handed people have and continue to die from operating equipment that was designed for right-handed people. Though I’ve had a hard time verifying this with numbers, I have found (even from practicing being left-handed) that there are tons of products that are poorly designed for left-handed people. We as designers must consider every outlier of use cases that ultimately includes every able and inable bodied persons out there. Accessability is still an issue when we consider every state, every user, every capability… We can run our budgets to the ground with trying to cover all bases. But if you neglect inclusivity, you are essentially designing a wall to block someone from your creation. This is true with everything from gender bias, racial acceptance, cultural differences, financial classes, there always seems to be something that drives other humans to be “separate” from another group. People will even research something in bias just to prove a point, only representing things that make that report look good. Others blatantly exclude others because of minor differences in choice, appearance, orientation, etc. This leads to empowering disgusting excuses for human beings. Nothing trumps the good intentions of people more than biased hatred in the world. As someone who was raised kind of sheltered to the world, in a good home, with morals, I’m constantly shocked by the actions of others. Though I am not perfect myself, I try to see things from the views of others, and am shocked by how prevalent the disparity between two seemingly different groups of people echo through our design world. Think of the fact that gender roles have been a “conventional ‘Male’ and ‘Female’ choice” as an old “ism” that we have kept. We could just alphabetize the option or kill it entirely from our forms. I recognize the needs for medical use as another issue, but for most daily use in design, that data is unnecessary. We need to avoid designing our work to favor any particular group and their ability, enabling them to perceive themselves as “ahead of” or “above another” human being. The data exists to be able to design our things to include others. Disparity doesn’t stop, unless we help stop it. We’re all made of the same stuff, born the same way, and we will all die the same. The thing about ethics is that we think that it’s too much to deal with, or that there’s no way to change the way the world works. That is not true. We can defeat disparity through our careers as designers. We need to focus on being a more effective designer, working on mastering the founding principles and holding you and the community accountable for what you all design. I think we will have the power to change the world. I will continue to improve my own skills and pass along that knowledge to others. Remember keep your ethics in check and help educate those you can. Take charge, and make change happen. Design Ethics Design Thinking UX Marketing By clapping more or less, you can signal to us which stories really stand out. Darian Rosebrook Brand Identity Designer for @itssomagnetic, running a design community at @compassofdesign. I write to help others grow their skills as designers. Compass of Design Some of the best design articles written by members of the Compass of Design Community to help you strengthen your design skills, business/freelance ethics, and design professionalism. Join us in the community or get on the newsletter to get access to exclusive content.</summary></entry></feed>