<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-11-29T21:14:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Portfolio</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tyrel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/tyrel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tyrel" /><published>2016-11-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-11-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/tyrel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/tyrel">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/growyourcode&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-twitter&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://growyourcode.com&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-globe&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;Podcast&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://keyspark.io&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-globe&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Twitter | Podcast | twitter</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the 1%</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/Welcome-to-the-1-Percent" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the 1%" /><published>2016-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/Welcome-to-the-1-Percent</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/Welcome-to-the-1-Percent">&lt;p&gt;The internet is a powerful tool for getting information. There are tens of millions of articles being consumed every day across the globe. Nearly 5 billion videos are watched on YouTube every day. It has never been easier than now to start creating things to put on the internet; yet, nearly 99% of the internet never do. Here’s where you come in.
The 1% rule of internet culture
“The 1% rule states that the number of people who create content on the Internet represents approximately 1% of the people actually viewing that content” — Wikipedia
This article from Wikipedia states further that the balance is closer to 90% — 9% — 1%, where the 90 percent are those who only lurk around, consuming content. The other 10 percent are those who contribute anything, and the last 1 percent of the internet are responsible for nearly all the content on the internet. Between comments, posts, videos, questions, websites. Almost everyone in that ten percent contribute something. It’s the 1% that is ruling the content we consume daily.
It is those that produce content that have the greatest advantage.
Work yourself out of the shadows
So how do you move out of the shadows? Isn’t everything on the internet just noise? Yes. Yes, it is. But the only thing you need to do is start. You will never climb out of the shadows if you don’t contribute. Start something that can be easily managed, and something that can be put up on a consistent basis.
I started a Twitter account back at the beginning of 2016 to be able to post design related content. Something I could use to front face my design work. After a while, someone recognized there was potential and invited me to Dribbble and I started writing here on Medium.
Is it easy to post things? No. A large portion of the time I have been inconsistent or sharing inconsistent to my agenda. I wanted to get my brand out there and build a reputation. What I didn’t realize is that was already starting. As I started to share more often, it became easier to create more content. It just took time.
The call for curating your content&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sea of content out there floating around. Most of those who are creating content already run a blog, they market on Instagram or social media, post to Dribbble and YouTube. What holds a lot of them back is posting only the things they are interested in. Anyone who has followers on their accounts, when you post a piece of content, you are sharing something that impacts your audience.
After an undetermined amount of time, it will become obvious to what kind of content is performing better than others. You have to understand who you are trying to reach and what their goals are. This goes back to a point I was trying to make when building a brand in my previous post about brand success. You need to have a greater understanding of your products, services, and the audience you are trying to reach.
Don’t think you don’t have anything to share
Your experience is unique. Everything you have gone through to this point has shaped your view on whatever it is that you do. What people fail to realize is the experiences that you have can help anyone on a similar road to you. If you have gone through countless tutorials to teach yourself design, you already know some of the pain points people have when they start out with self teaching. Maybe you’re from a social, racial, political, or majority group that experiences a difficulty most other groups don’t when doing what you do. The point is to never think you don’t have something to contribute. Move into the 1 percent.
What to expect when creating content
Let’s get back to the rule of the 1%. You need to have realistic expectations when creating content on the internet.
No one noticed anything I was posting during my first two months of new content. I had an audience that consisted of my mom, cat, girlfriend and twenty or so spam bots that followed me from a hashtag I put out on my first post. Eventually I started to build an audience around the design related content I was sharing. After that undetermined amount of time, (really, that amount of time is dictated by yourself and your own perception of your audience. A post for another time.) I started to notice a trend going on. Of the posts that were well received, my content was only getting about 2–10% engagement from my audience.
Researching this trend further led me to find that this wasn’t only my content that receives this level of engagement. I poured over 400 pieces of content consisting of YouTube Videos, Dribbble shots, and email statistics that others around me were posting as well. I thankfully had some ways of automating this task, but still, I went over 200 of the Dribbble shots by hand to get some stats on the levels of engagement you’ll expect from what kind of content you’re posting.
Though I know that likes don’t count for all the versions and levels of engagement, this was my first discovery of metrics, and what I chose to track for some of the sites. (I’ll be releasing this data in a future post)
Dribbble.com seemed to be the higher range of engagement with the number of likes vs. the number of views
Of the people that I follow with inclusion of my content, the likes to view count came to:
Total views of: 256, 487
Total Likes of: 16, 146
For a total of 6.3% engagement.
The most popular shots from all the people on Dribbble came to this:
Total views of: 73,968
Total likes of: 6,337
For a total of 8.57% engagement
YouTube was on the lower end of the spectrum with:
Total views of: 1,398,544,432
Total likes of: 31,130,855
For a total of 2.02% engagement.
Even from MailChimp’s Email Marketing Benchmarks, there was an average click through rate of 2.66%.
What can you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build up that backlog of content. You position yourself as part of the top contributing members of society. Though you may feel a bit vulnerable putting out tiny pieces of yourself, your ability to help people out there will be a great advantage for you as a professional. Though the numbers will seem small and insignificant, your audience still grows slowly or quickly based on your ability to sense what your target audience wants. All this builds upon your own experience which then you get to share further and further towards mastery.
With mastery, you are able to:
Charge more for the value of your products or services
Hone in on the audience that you are best equipped to help
Become better with promoting your brand and the content you produce
Become better at converting the consumers of your content to your customers or supporters.
The only thing that’s holding you back from being part of the 1% is you.
Get out there and create!
Darian Rosebrook is the Design Lead over at keyspark.io His creative eye is driving us forward as an ever-growing, ever-improving brand.
You can follow our articles here on medium or join us on twitter!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">The internet is a powerful tool for getting information. There are tens of millions of articles being consumed every day across the globe. Nearly 5 billion videos are watched on YouTube every day. It has never been easier than now to start creating things to put on the internet; yet, nearly 99% of the internet never do. Here’s where you come in.
The 1% rule of internet culture
“The 1% rule states that the number of people who create content on the Internet represents approximately 1% of the people actually viewing that content” — Wikipedia
This article from Wikipedia states further that the balance is closer to 90% — 9% — 1%, where the 90 percent are those who only lurk around, consuming content. The other 10 percent are those who contribute anything, and the last 1 percent of the internet are responsible for nearly all the content on the internet. Between comments, posts, videos, questions, websites. Almost everyone in that ten percent contribute something. It’s the 1% that is ruling the content we consume daily.
It is those that produce content that have the greatest advantage.
Work yourself out of the shadows
So how do you move out of the shadows? Isn’t everything on the internet just noise? Yes. Yes, it is. But the only thing you need to do is start. You will never climb out of the shadows if you don’t contribute. Start something that can be easily managed, and something that can be put up on a consistent basis.
I started a Twitter account back at the beginning of 2016 to be able to post design related content. Something I could use to front face my design work. After a while, someone recognized there was potential and invited me to Dribbble and I started writing here on Medium.
Is it easy to post things? No. A large portion of the time I have been inconsistent or sharing inconsistent to my agenda. I wanted to get my brand out there and build a reputation. What I didn’t realize is that was already starting. As I started to share more often, it became easier to create more content. It just took time.
The call for curating your content</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darian Rosebrook Portfolio</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/portfolio-website" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darian Rosebrook Portfolio" /><published>2016-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/portfolio-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/portfolio-website"></content><category term="[&quot;case-study&quot;, &quot;public&quot;, &quot;web&quot;]" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darian Rosebrook Portfolio Branding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/portfolio-branding" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darian Rosebrook Portfolio Branding" /><published>2016-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/portfolio-branding</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/portfolio-branding"></content><category term="[&quot;case-study&quot;, &quot;public&quot;, &quot;brand&quot;]" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 Ways to Guide Your Brand Towards Success</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/4-ways-to-guide-your-brand-towards-success" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 Ways to Guide Your Brand Towards Success" /><published>2016-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/4-ways-to-guide-your-brand-towards-success</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/4-ways-to-guide-your-brand-towards-success">&lt;p&gt;Setting your brand in motion can be scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gif from: Giphy
Of course, for many people, running a business itself is a scary concept. But knowing that your brand message and purpose is unified, there is no reason you should worry about how your brand is received by your customers.
Here are four areas to evaluate if your brand is unified:
Messaging&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image from Unsplash
How your brand uses language to communicate your products, services, and advertising can impact how your brand stands with your customers. The words you use can work for you or against you. To figure out which side your messaging falls on; it is important to do the proper research. How do the words you choose to present your products and services help or hinder your brand?
The easiest way to figure this out is to look for your target audience and understand how they communicate. Is the audience using certain lingo that your brand doesn’t focus on? Trying too hard to market to this group can be easily detected. Unless you’re a company that started from within your target audience, the best way of understanding your audience is to do your research.
Ask yourself “is your message is being received as it is intended”? Even with the right lingo, you could be sending the wrong message about your company. Cultural differences and language barriers are other ways where your message could “get lost in translation”. So doing a review on what words your company is using can greatly improve the impact you have on your target audience.
Logo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image from unsplash
A logo is the face of a brand. For many companies it’s the only thing separating their products and services from an overseas equivalent. It makes sense to invest in a logo that can carry a brand for decades to come. You’ll invest exactly how much you believe in your own products and services. An investment in a company’s logo could involve a five dollar logo service, a freelancer, an agency, or an old acquaintance from art school. Every level of service is different and serves your brand’s purpose in a different way.
Your logo serves the purpose of creating an easy-to-identify mark that uniquely represents your business. It’s important that the symbol you choose creates a good impression with your audience. A good designer researches the industry to make sure that the design will be current, timeless and aligned to the goals of your company. It is easy to try and shortcut this process; which can end up hurting your brand in the long run. A quick search on the internet for “logo mistakes” can represent why it’s important to invest in a great design process.
Branding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image from Unsplash
The logo you choose for your company is just a child of a bigger system. You see this when you think of larger companies. Industry giants know the importance of having their image unified under a specific brand. It goes much deeper than slapping your logo onto a cup. Your customer pays for the experience they get when choosing you over the competitor. They chose your coffee stand because of the logo you have. They chose your magazine because it’s the company that uses brash sarcasm in its marketing. A unique experience is the key to sending your brand to the top.
Design agencies specialize in creating this type of experience for your brand. A great brand guideline acts as a filter for new ideas and for your products. You can reach a high level of brand recognition with an investment in unifying your brand.
Content&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image from Unsplash
The idea of reaching your audience through content marketing is not new. Creating consistent content is still a great way to help your customers more than your competition. The way you run your company should reflect a greater understanding of your products, services, and the audience you are trying to reach. Having a platform to share this knowledge is important for the way you drive interest to your company.
What is important to understand is that having content, for the sake of content, is just noise. If you are putting out content for the purpose of seeming knowledgeable; your audience will see right through it. A company that has deep history is better equipped to understand the needs of their audience. Having resources dedicated for customer support is helpful. Even having your company on social media and an e-mailing list equips your company with the resources to survey or respond to questions. The difficult part is answering them in a way that allows everyone to benefit from the answer. Fulfilling those needs with the medium you choose: a website, email, or social media, it should be put through your brand guidelines to unify your brand.
Each step involved is one that we’ve taken at KeySpark to improve our brand. We want to help other companies achieve their next level of brand awareness.
Please leave us a comment, or send us a message, on how you think we can help you and your brand succeed.
Darian Rosebrook is the Design Lead over at keyspark.io His creative eye is driving us forward as an ever-growing, ever-improving brand.
You can follow our articles here on medium or join us on twitter!
@keyspark_io&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Setting your brand in motion can be scary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grow Your Code Update</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/grow-your-code-update" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grow Your Code Update" /><published>2016-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/grow-your-code-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/grow-your-code-update"></content><category term="[&quot;case-study&quot;, &quot;public&quot;, &quot;brand&quot;]" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">keySpark Branding Update</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/keyspark-brand-update" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="keySpark Branding Update" /><published>2016-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/keyspark-brand-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/keyspark-brand-update"></content><category term="[&quot;case-study&quot;, &quot;public&quot;, &quot;brand&quot;]" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stop saying ‘Yes’ to Everything</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/stop-saying-yes-to-everything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop saying 'Yes' to Everything" /><published>2016-10-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-10-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/stop-saying-yes-to-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/stop-saying-yes-to-everything">&lt;p&gt;The internet is a powerful tool for getting information. There are tens of millions of articles being consumed every day across the globe. Nearly 5 billion videos are watched on YouTube every day. It has never been easier than now to start creating things to put on the internet; yet, nearly 99% of the internet never do. Here’s where you come in.
The 1% rule of internet culture
“The 1% rule states that the number of people who create content on the Internet represents approximately 1% of the people actually viewing that content” — Wikipedia
This article from Wikipedia states further that the balance is closer to 90% — 9% — 1%, where the 90 percent are those who only lurk around, consuming content. The other 10 percent are those who contribute anything, and the last 1 percent of the internet are responsible for nearly all the content on the internet. Between comments, posts, videos, questions, websites. Almost everyone in that ten percent contribute something. It’s the 1% that is ruling the content we consume daily.
It is those that produce content that have the greatest advantage.
Work yourself out of the shadows
So how do you move out of the shadows? Isn’t everything on the internet just noise? Yes. Yes, it is. But the only thing you need to do is start. You will never climb out of the shadows if you don’t contribute. Start something that can be easily managed, and something that can be put up on a consistent basis.
I started a Twitter account back at the beginning of 2016 to be able to post design related content. Something I could use to front face my design work. After a while, someone recognized there was potential and invited me to Dribbble and I started writing here on Medium.
Is it easy to post things? No. A large portion of the time I have been inconsistent or sharing inconsistent to my agenda. I wanted to get my brand out there and build a reputation. What I didn’t realize is that was already starting. As I started to share more often, it became easier to create more content. It just took time.
The call for curating your content&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sea of content out there floating around. Most of those who are creating content already run a blog, they market on Instagram or social media, post to Dribbble and YouTube. What holds a lot of them back is posting only the things they are interested in. Anyone who has followers on their accounts, when you post a piece of content, you are sharing something that impacts your audience.
After an undetermined amount of time, it will become obvious to what kind of content is performing better than others. You have to understand who you are trying to reach and what their goals are. This goes back to a point I was trying to make when building a brand in my previous post about brand success. You need to have a greater understanding of your products, services, and the audience you are trying to reach.
Don’t think you don’t have anything to share
Your experience is unique. Everything you have gone through to this point has shaped your view on whatever it is that you do. What people fail to realize is the experiences that you have can help anyone on a similar road to you. If you have gone through countless tutorials to teach yourself design, you already know some of the pain points people have when they start out with self teaching. Maybe you’re from a social, racial, political, or majority group that experiences a difficulty most other groups don’t when doing what you do. The point is to never think you don’t have something to contribute. Move into the 1 percent.
What to expect when creating content
Let’s get back to the rule of the 1%. You need to have realistic expectations when creating content on the internet.
No one noticed anything I was posting during my first two months of new content. I had an audience that consisted of my mom, cat, girlfriend and twenty or so spam bots that followed me from a hashtag I put out on my first post. Eventually I started to build an audience around the design related content I was sharing. After that undetermined amount of time, (really, that amount of time is dictated by yourself and your own perception of your audience. A post for another time.) I started to notice a trend going on. Of the posts that were well received, my content was only getting about 2–10% engagement from my audience.
Researching this trend further led me to find that this wasn’t only my content that receives this level of engagement. I poured over 400 pieces of content consisting of YouTube Videos, Dribbble shots, and email statistics that others around me were posting as well. I thankfully had some ways of automating this task, but still, I went over 200 of the Dribbble shots by hand to get some stats on the levels of engagement you’ll expect from what kind of content you’re posting.
Though I know that likes don’t count for all the versions and levels of engagement, this was my first discovery of metrics, and what I chose to track for some of the sites. (I’ll be releasing this data in a future post)
Dribbble.com seemed to be the higher range of engagement with the number of likes vs. the number of views
Of the people that I follow with inclusion of my content, the likes to view count came to:
Total views of: 256, 487
Total Likes of: 16, 146
For a total of 6.3% engagement.
The most popular shots from all the people on Dribbble came to this:
Total views of: 73,968
Total likes of: 6,337
For a total of 8.57% engagement
YouTube was on the lower end of the spectrum with:
Total views of: 1,398,544,432
Total likes of: 31,130,855
For a total of 2.02% engagement.
Even from MailChimp’s Email Marketing Benchmarks, there was an average click through rate of 2.66%.
What can you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build up that backlog of content. You position yourself as part of the top contributing members of society. Though you may feel a bit vulnerable putting out tiny pieces of yourself, your ability to help people out there will be a great advantage for you as a professional. Though the numbers will seem small and insignificant, your audience still grows slowly or quickly based on your ability to sense what your target audience wants. All this builds upon your own experience which then you get to share further and further towards mastery.
With mastery, you are able to:
Charge more for the value of your products or services
Hone in on the audience that you are best equipped to help
Become better with promoting your brand and the content you produce
Become better at converting the consumers of your content to your customers or supporters.
The only thing that’s holding you back from being part of the 1% is you.
Get out there and create!
Darian Rosebrook is the Design Lead over at keyspark.io His creative eye is driving us forward as an ever-growing, ever-improving brand.
You can follow our articles here on medium or join us on twitter!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">The internet is a powerful tool for getting information. There are tens of millions of articles being consumed every day across the globe. Nearly 5 billion videos are watched on YouTube every day. It has never been easier than now to start creating things to put on the internet; yet, nearly 99% of the internet never do. Here’s where you come in.
The 1% rule of internet culture
“The 1% rule states that the number of people who create content on the Internet represents approximately 1% of the people actually viewing that content” — Wikipedia
This article from Wikipedia states further that the balance is closer to 90% — 9% — 1%, where the 90 percent are those who only lurk around, consuming content. The other 10 percent are those who contribute anything, and the last 1 percent of the internet are responsible for nearly all the content on the internet. Between comments, posts, videos, questions, websites. Almost everyone in that ten percent contribute something. It’s the 1% that is ruling the content we consume daily.
It is those that produce content that have the greatest advantage.
Work yourself out of the shadows
So how do you move out of the shadows? Isn’t everything on the internet just noise? Yes. Yes, it is. But the only thing you need to do is start. You will never climb out of the shadows if you don’t contribute. Start something that can be easily managed, and something that can be put up on a consistent basis.
I started a Twitter account back at the beginning of 2016 to be able to post design related content. Something I could use to front face my design work. After a while, someone recognized there was potential and invited me to Dribbble and I started writing here on Medium.
Is it easy to post things? No. A large portion of the time I have been inconsistent or sharing inconsistent to my agenda. I wanted to get my brand out there and build a reputation. What I didn’t realize is that was already starting. As I started to share more often, it became easier to create more content. It just took time.
The call for curating your content</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Great designs are measured by the questions asked before the work.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/great-designers-are-measured" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Great designs are measured by the questions asked before the work." /><published>2016-09-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/great-designers-are-measured</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/great-designers-are-measured">&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! You have a new project in the pipeline. It may have been a while or it may have been a short amount of time since your last work as a designer, but one thing we all know about design is that you have to understand what is really going on inside the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint: take notes when you ask inportant things
Understanding a project is a vital part of what we do in the design industrial. For us to be able to deliver on a project in a way that addresses it’s specific need and delivers value to it’s audience, you have to be able to ask great questions.
What makes a “great question?”
Well that’s a great question! (Sorry, I had to.) The reason a question is asked is to get valuable information that you otherwise couldn’t obtain, but the quality of that value is determined by how effective that information is. You need to target your questions towards getting an open ended response, not just a binary ‘yes’ or ‘no.’
It is important that you know the distinction between these types so that asking open ended questions for the intent of answering a need becomes second nature to you. There are questions that may seem open ended but are really just filler questions. Those ones like “What do you want for dinner?” or “What is your favorite color?” usually equate to single response answers. (BTW: pizza and forest green #424f42)
The sweet spot is in finding the balance between specific question and open ended. “What are your existing brand assets?” hits that spot by understanding part of your needs as a designer to deliver quality work is to attain the files for the project. What makes this a quality question is that it leaves it open for answers that you may not have been expecting. You’ll only learn to do this by using open ended questions more often; so get to practicing.
What are you trying to solve?
When starting to ask questions, you need to be writing the answers down. So grab your favorite pen and sit down somewhere and ask people anything. Your goal is to get to the heart of the issue as quick as possible. A cheap but effective question that does this is the only broad open ended question you should really ask is “why?”
I hear this often on the seanwes network
“How to get to the core of something: ask why until the answer stops changing.”
You can use this when you feel like your information that you receive from a question doesn’t solve what you need to. If someone is saying “I need a website for my business” you can ask why until you get to the underlying reason. Maybe they need a website because all the foot traffic for that business has gone down because everyone is ordering online now… you never know until you ask.
Don’t ‘ask questions’ for the sake of asking them.
Open communication will lead to a successful design. But you want to be sure that you’re being efficient and direct with the questions you ask. If your goal is to increase the conversion of online shoppers, asking “what fish do you usually catch during the summer” is not an efficient way of getting that answer. You have to understand your goal to understand which questions to continue with.
I’m not saying that fish question won’t help you understand the person you’re working for and their preference at all. But if your client’s target audience has issues with fishing or harming animals of any kind, having a spot for the client’s fishing habit is actually going to work against the effectiveness of the design. Also answering questions is taxing on the attention span of your client and your audience, so having things streamlined will lean towards improving the quality of your overall answers.
As you tally down your list of questions, understand that it’s okay to ask more about the project as you go along. Remember that list of questions is going to change as you figure out what works and what doesn’t.
What questions have worked for you (or not worked for you) in the past?
Leave a comment below and help out by recommending this to a friend!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="article" /><summary type="html">Congratulations! You have a new project in the pipeline. It may have been a while or it may have been a short amount of time since your last work as a designer, but one thing we all know about design is that you have to understand what is really going on inside the project.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Timo’s Tacos Concept</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archive/timos-tacos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Timo's Tacos Concept" /><published>2016-09-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archive/timos-tacos</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archive/timos-tacos"></content><category term="[&quot;case-study&quot;, &quot;public&quot;, &quot;Branding&quot;]" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>
